<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Peppa, or, The reward of constant love a novel : done out of French : with several songs set to musick for two voices / by a young-gentlewoman.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 164 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54291</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1448</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20576</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12355376</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12355376</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60133</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54291)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60133)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 220:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Peppa, or, The reward of constant love a novel : done out of French : with several songs set to musick for two voices / by a young-gentlewoman.</title>
                  <author>A. C.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 120, [11] p. : music.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Crooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Licensed, 1689. James Fraser."</note>
                  <note>Dedication "To the Honourable the Lady Isabella Roberts" signed: A.C.</note>
                  <note>Advertisements on p. [1]-[10] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Songs, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60133:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60133:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Peppa: OR, The REWARD OF CONSTANT LOVE.</p>
            <p>A NOVEL.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="blackletterType">Done out of</hi> French.</p>
            <p>With ſeveral SONGS ſet to MU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SICK, for TWO VOICES.</p>
            <p>By a Young-Gentlewoman.</p>
            <p>Licenſed, 1689.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>JAMES FRASER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Crooke</hi> at the <hi>Green-Dragon</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:60133:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60133:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOURABLE THE LADY <hi>ISABELLA ROBERTS.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT was a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Time before I could reſolve up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Dedication; but,
<pb facs="tcp:60133:3"/> knowing that few Books, (and eſpecially <hi>Novels,</hi>) are wanting in this Point, I then preſently fix'd my Reſolution; trod in the ſteps of thoſe that went before; and ſubmitted to the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Cuſtom. I was not long in reſolving to whom I ought to dedicate it: Your Honour became in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly the Object of a Thought lofty, and
<pb facs="tcp:60133:3"/> aſpiring, which hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried me to this Bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Yes, Madam, you will think it is a new way of being grateful for paſt Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, to ask new ones: And yet this very Abſurdity do I now commit; but I am ſenſible of your generous Temper, and relying upon that alone, I beg this one Favour more, your Patronage, and
<pb facs="tcp:60133:4"/> Acceptance of this Virgin Eſſay, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of my leiſure Hours.</p>
            <p>This piece in all its Deſigns, aims at what is great and generous, and is founded partly upon Truth; many of the material Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances having been really acted at <hi>Genoa</hi> but few years a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go: It inſiſts chiefly upon two Subjects;
<pb facs="tcp:60133:4"/> the effects of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parallel'd Friendſhip; and the Force, and Reward of Conſtant Love. It appear'd firſt of all in <hi>French;</hi> and tho now naturaliz'd into our good-na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd Climat, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>Engliſh,</hi> yet it has loſt nothing of its <hi>French</hi> Vanity, and Preſumption, but da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly hopes to crow'd into your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour's Cloſet, there
<pb facs="tcp:60133:5"/> expecting the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Time when, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, you will be pleas'd to throw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſome ſpare mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>Thoſe Readers who have not yet been bleſs'd with your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour's Acquaintance, may perhaps ſay, This is not like a Dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and their Reaſon for it will be, becauſe it is not ſtuff'd with ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
<pb facs="tcp:60133:5"/> Flattery, and becauſe I have not deſcrib'd to 'em either your Perſon, or Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues; but I muſt tell them (whoſoever they may be) that I am a very ill Encomiaſt, and a worſe Flatterer: However, rather than Men ſhould go away diſcontented, if in few words a plain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable Truth will ſatisfy 'em, they ſhall have it; that your
<pb facs="tcp:60133:6"/> Birth, Nature, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpir'd together to make you every way truly agreeable, which, tho it has procur'd you the ſtrongeſt Envy of our Sex, it has attract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no leſs the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Admiration of theirs.</p>
            <p>One Favour more I importunely crave, that for ſome Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb facs="tcp:60133:6"/> (which by you, Madam, ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded from me at any time,) I may be permitted to refrain the publiſhing my Name in Print; tho really nothing is ſo ſenſible a Grief to me, as that I am forc'd to ſtifle my greateſt Ambition, which is, to declare to the World, the Name of her, who, among all the Crowd of
<pb facs="tcp:60133:7"/> your Admirers, is the moſt zealouſly,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Honour's Moſt Humble, Moſt Faithful, And moſt devoted Servant, A. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60133:7"/>
            <head>PEPPA: OR, THE REWARD OF CONSTANT LOVE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>GEnoa</hi> is a City of <hi>Italy,</hi> not leſs famous for its Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty than for the flouriſhing Condition it is in at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, maintain'd chiefly by a Commerce, and good Correſpondence with almoſt all the Nations of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe; and is now eſteem'd one of the richeſt Towns in <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As this City is very Ancient, ſo there is in it many Illuſtrious Families, and ſome that are allied to Soveraign Princes, amongſt whom, the Prince
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60133:8"/> 
               <hi>Mark Antony Doria</hi> made no ſmall Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, being in as great eſteem for his vaſt Riches and Poſſeſſions, as for the Nobility of his Anceſtors; and having an earneſt deſire in theſe latter Times, to make the Glory of his Family ſhine out in his own Perſon, he apply'd his youthful Time and Courage, for ſome years, in the Service of the <hi>Spaniard;</hi> but not meeting with thoſe Honourable Rewards which his Courage had meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he diſcontentedly retir'd to <hi>Genoa;</hi> where, ſome little time after, he marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Siſter of the Marqueſs <hi>Durazzo,</hi> a perſon of an exquiſite Beauty. All People look'd upon this Marriage as ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry happy, ſeeing the aſſiduous care the Prince <hi>Doria</hi> took to pleaſe his Wife, who in requital lov'd him with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream Paſſion. About a year after they were married, ſhe was deliver'd of a Daughter; but her lying in was follow'd with a Conſequence ſo fatal, that tho all means were us'd, ſhe relaps'd into a great weakneſs of Body, and, after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving languiſh'd five or ſix Months, dy'd. The Prince was ſo ſenſibly touch'd with this loſs, that he withdrew himſelf for a long time into a Monaſtery, without ſeeing any body, avoiding even thoſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60133:8"/> very perſons who were only capable of giving him ſome Comfort. The little Princeſs, who was nam'd <hi>Peppa,</hi> was brought up under the Tuition of her Aunt the Marchioneſs <hi>Durazzo,</hi> who had a Daughter of the ſame age. The Prince <hi>Doria</hi> led a life very retir'd for four years, not endering to hear of a ſecond Marriage; nevertheleſs his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and Friends did urge him with ſuch preſſing Arguments, that having at length determin'd to give them ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, he courted a Lady of the Houſe of <hi>Spinola</hi> It was not long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he married her, but ſhe had never the fortune to be with Child; ſo that <hi>Peppa,</hi> who in her tender Infancy had already the marks of a perf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct Beauty, was look'd upon as one of the greateſt Fortunes of all <hi>Italy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Princeſs <hi>Doria,</hi> now after a ſeven years Marriage, deſpairing ever to give her Husband a Succeſſour, found ſome Comfort in thinking, that ſhe might one day unite the two Houſes of <hi>Doria</hi> and <hi>Spinola,</hi> by the Marriage of the young Marqueſs <hi>Spinola</hi> her N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>phew, with <hi>Peppa;</hi> and to the end that ſhe might have the opportunity of prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring betimes the Mind of <hi>Peppa,</hi> ſhe ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60133:9"/> entreated her Husband to recall his Daughter into his own Houſe, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring him, that ſhe had an extream af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection for her, and that ſhe did now look upon <hi>Peppa</hi> as her own Child. The Prince <hi>Doria</hi> lov'd his Daughter moſt entirely, was in an extaſy of joy to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the deſire of his Wife, and did not delay the ſatisfaction which ſhe deſir'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peppa</hi> was receiv'd into her Father's Houſe with all the Teſtimonies of Love and Affection that ſhe could expect from a Mother-in-law, who would be no longer ſuch towards her, for ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd her Husband to let <hi>Peppa</hi> call her Mother; and ſhe would give her the name of Daughter. <hi>Peppa,</hi> who was of a fine Wit, anſwer'd with an obliging readineſs to all the kindneſſes expreſs'd to her by her Mother-in-law. The Princeſs on her ſide did whatever ſhe thought would pleaſe her Daughter-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>law; and being inform'd that <hi>Peppa</hi> was much troubl'd to part with one of her Couſins which ſhe lov'd entirely; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he intreated the Marchioneſs <hi>Durazzo,</hi> to permit her Daughter <hi>Julia</hi> to be bred with <hi>Peppa</hi> in the Family of the Prince <hi>Doria.</hi> The Marchioneſs, who had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60133:9"/> Children, and could not maintain them according to their Quality, had deſign'd them Nuns. 'Twas for this reaſon, that with much difficulty ſhe was brought to yield, that <hi>Julia</hi> ſhould live with her Couſin. Nevertheleſs <hi>Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa</hi> wiſh'd it with ſo much eagerneſs, and her Relations, who had a great deal of kindneſs for her, ſo earneſtly deſir'd this of the Marchioneſs, that ſhe no longer oppos'd it. <hi>Peppa</hi> and <hi>Julia</hi> ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd not the diſpleaſure of being part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the delights of living always together, contributed ſtill further to the ſtrengthening that perfect Union which was between them. The Princeſs <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> who had her Intereſt in proſpect, let ſlip no opportunity of entertaining <hi>Peppa</hi> with the Grandure of the Houſe of <hi>Spinola,</hi> the famous Captains that it hath produc'd for the Honour of <hi>Italy,</hi> and a great many advantages conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that it had above the other Families of <hi>Genoa.</hi> She added, that ſhe was much deceiv'd if the young Marqueſs <hi>Spinola,</hi> who had already a delicate Meen, and a great deal of Wit, did not maintain with Splendor, the Glory of his Anceſtours. <hi>Peppa</hi> liſten'd to the diſcourſe of the Princeſs, without making
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60133:10"/> the leaſt Reflection; but in the end per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that they made the Marqueſs of <hi>Spinola</hi> be more than ordinary aſſiduous, in rendring her his Devoirs, and that her Mother-in-law, cunningly ingag'd to make now and then Appointments of Diverſions with the Marqueſs, ſhe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd to <hi>Julia</hi> of this conſtraint of her Humour, finding her ſelf only pleas'd when ſhe was in her company; and all the means that the Princeſs <hi>Doria</hi> us'd made <hi>Peppa</hi> have the greater averſion for the Marqueſs.</p>
            <p>In the mean while, tho <hi>Peppa</hi> was yet but fourteen years old, all that ſaw her, ſpoke of her Beauty with admiration; ſhe was of a fine ſhape, the Features of her Face were very delicate, curious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yes, a fine Skin, and ſhe had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing in her Face that was ſo taking, that it was impoſſible to look on her without having an infinite eſteem for her perſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Julia</hi> was not ſo perfect Beauty, but ſhe had much Spritelineſs, and not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Sweetneſs appear'd in the whole Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry of her Face. She would ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſay to her Couſin, That ſhe was of a different Humour from all other young Maids, who are always troubled
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60133:10"/> that they are not handſome enough, whereas nothing diſcompos'd her more than to hear the World ſay ſhe had Beauty; for had ſhe been depriv'd of it, ſhe could have quitted the World with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Regret, and paſt the reſt of her life in a Convent, as ſhe was deſign'd. <hi>Peppa</hi> endeavour'd to comfort her, by letting her know, that ſhe was not made for the Cloiſter, and that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing might happen which would cauſe a change in the Will of her Parents.</p>
            <p>The fame of <hi>Peppa</hi>'s Beauty was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried over all <hi>Italy,</hi> and that ſhe was the only Heireſs to the Houſe of <hi>Doria.</hi> All theſe reaſons oblig'd ſeveral Perſons of eminent Quality to eſteem the Poſſeſſion of her to be a Fortune that would crown their utmoſt deſire. There was one, even a Soveraign Prince, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd her for his Son, but the Princeſs <hi>Doria</hi> rais'd ſecretly ſo many difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that the buſineſs was at laſt broke off. The Marqueſs <hi>Spinola,</hi> who found <hi>Peppa</hi> very agreeable, and perceiv'd the great advantages that would accrue to him by this Alliance, made it his whole ſtudy to pleaſe her; and now through his own Inclination he began really to love her, who till then had but ſeemingly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60133:11"/> done it, out of compliance to his Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. He perceiv'd that <hi>Peppa</hi> was not in the leaſt touch'd with his Love, which made him reſolve to try, whether he could not take the advantage of the <hi>Carnaval-time,</hi> for to give to his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs the moſt publick marks of the Paſſion he had for her. This <hi>Carnaval</hi> is a time of Rejoicing, (or rather, mad Frolicks) in moſt Countries of <hi>Europe,</hi> (eſpecially among the <hi>Romaniſts</hi>), and laſts from <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> till <hi>Shrove-Tueſday</hi> at night, at which time their madneſs ends; for which, during the <hi>Lent,</hi> they ſeem to do Penance: This is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing agreeable to an old <hi>Engliſh</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb; <hi>Sweet Meats will have ſower Sauce.</hi> But to return to our Marqueſs, he came to all the Balls with a magnificent Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance. There he danc'd ſeveral times with <hi>Peppa;</hi> and when ſhe retir'd, he took care that ſeveral Violins ſhould always attend her Coach to the Door, and there ſtay the greateſt part of the night. Nevertheleſs, as all things ſeem inſipid to a perſon that has no Taſt, <hi>Peppa</hi> made no returns to his preſſing So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitations, and acknowledg'd to <hi>Julia,</hi> in private, that ſhe did not find her ſelf at all diſpos'd to receive Addreſſes from
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60133:11"/> the Marqueſs, and that ſhe well foreſaw, ſhe ſhould be the moſt unhappy perſon in the World, if her Parents did oblige her to marry him.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Chevalier</hi> of—and another <hi>French</hi> Gentleman, by chance happen'd to be at <hi>Genoa</hi> during this <hi>Carnaval,</hi> and going to ſeveral Balls in Maſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rade, as being the Cuſtom of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; they, hearing that there was to be at the Palace of the Marqueſs <hi>Juſtiniano</hi> a great Feaſt, which was to be concluded with a Ball, were reſolv'd to go thither, diſguis'd in the form of Sea-Monſters. It being an unuſual ſort of Maſquerade, every one was ſtrangely ſurpris'd to ſee a ſpectacle ſo extraordinary, and which frighten'd ſome of the Ladies; the two Gentlemen perceiving it, they untied only a ſmall ſtring, by the help where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they ſlipp'd out of their monſtrous Habit, and appear'd extreamly gallant. The <hi>Chevalier</hi> of—was one of the handſomeſt Men in the World, and his ſhape was not leſs admirable, which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted the Eyes of all that were preſent. They both danc'd with a very good Grace, and particularly the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> that the other Gentlemen durſt ſcarce dance after him. All the Aſſembly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60133:12"/> not a little ſatisfy'd, crowning them with all the Applauſe imaginable. The <hi>Chevalier</hi> of—having obſerv'd that <hi>Peppa</hi> and <hi>Julia</hi> were in diſcourſe with two other Ladies, went and plac'd himſelf by them. The Ladies gave him infinite praiſes, aſſuring him, that they never ſaw a Man ſo gentilely habited, nor that danc'd ſo finely. The <hi>Chevalier</hi> anſwer'd very modeſtly to all their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliments, but with a great deal of Wit. The Ladies, who knew him not, and were ignorant even of what Nation he was, becauſe he ſpoke very well their Language, were very curious of his Acquaintance. They had all no ſmall reſpect for his Perſon, and the more he utter'd any thing that charm'd theſe La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, the more their Curioſity encreas'd: At laſt it came to that, that they deſir'd him to take off his Mask for a moment. The <hi>Chevalier,</hi> who was ſatisfy'd that they did not know him, had the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſance to do what they deſir'd, and let them ſee a Face, which if diſagreeing with the reſt of his perſon, was only ſo by being too handſome. He put on his Mask again not long after, and remain'd ſome time converſing with them. He obſerv'd <hi>Peppa</hi> very at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentively,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60133:12"/> and thought her the moſt beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Creature that he had ever ſeen. He began to take a great delight in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing near her, and was juſt about exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all the Features of her Face, when the Marqueſs <hi>Spinola</hi> came to deſire her to dance. <hi>Peppa,</hi> who was in diſcourſe with the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> and not a little pleas'd with it, was ſo troubled at the Marqueſs's Compliment, that, tho ſhe roſe to give him her Hand, ſhe ſcarce knew what ſhe did; and ſhe had not danc'd long before ſhe was ſeiz'd with ſuch a Faintneſs, that forc'd her to quit the Ball before it was ended. The <hi>Chevalier</hi> of—went out preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the next morning went aboard his own Veſſel to return to <hi>France,</hi> where he diſcours'd to all his Friends of the charming Creature that he had ſeen at <hi>Genoa;</hi> he himſelf wondring at the ſame time, how he could command himſelf ſo far as to leave her, and take a Reſolution of departing. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, as he was no leſs skilful in Muſick and Poetry, than in the Dance, he had not the power to withſtand ſome ſoft moments, wherein he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd ſeveral Sonnets in praiſe of the fair <hi>Peppa;</hi> among which here is one.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="song">
               <body>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:60133:13"/>
                  <lg n="1">
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> WHen <hi>Phillis</hi> firſt I ſaw, that lovely Maid,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> how great was my ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> She in a moment did my Heart invade,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> wi'th' Magick of her Eyes:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> She in a moment did my Heart invade,</l>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:60133:13"/>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> wi'th' Magick of her Eyes;</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> wi'th' Magick of her Eyes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="2">
                     <head>2.</head>
                     <l>Approach I did, but with ſo great an Awe,</l>
                     <l>I trembling ſpeechleſs ſtood:</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nuſual heat did all my Veins o'reflow,</l>
                     <l>Then chill'd was all my Blood.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Unuſual,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="3">
                     <head>3.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Confuſion did my Reſolution bind,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Scarce could I ſpeak, or move:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Deſpair had took poſſeſſion of my Mind,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And check'd my hopes of Love.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Deſpair, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:60133:14"/>
            <p>As ſoon as <hi>Peppa</hi> was alone with her Couſin, ſhe unboſom'd her thoughts to her, and declar'd, That ſhe would never pardon the Marqueſs <hi>Spinola</hi> the ſenſible diſpleaſure he had done her, by his interrupting the Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which they had with the Stranger, whom they found ſo obliging. <hi>Have you ever ſeen,</hi> continu'd <hi>Peppa, a Man ſo handſome, that had ſo fine a Wit, and ſo agreeable, and that danc'd with ſuch a Majeſtick Air? If we had diſcours'd long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er with him,</hi> interrupted <hi>Julia, we might perhaps have diſcover'd who he was. I muſt needs own,</hi> cry'd <hi>Peppa,</hi> bluſhing, <hi>the ſight of him has made no ſmall impreſſion in my Thoughts, and not to make any further ſecret of it between us, I cann't but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that ever ſince that time I have felt ſuch emotions, whereof till then I was wholly ignorant. In the mean time I don't know him, neither can I tell the Countrey he is of, and perhaps we ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſee him more.</hi> Theſe laſt words were ended with a ſigh, which diſcover'd, that this Stranger was not indifferent to her, and altho her Couſin gave her ſome hopes that ſhe might meet him at another Ball, yet this hope was too weak to bring her much Comfort. Theſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60133:14"/> two Ladies met at almoſt all the divert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Paſtimes that were perform'd at <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noa,</hi> during the time of the <hi>Carnaval. Peppa,</hi> who found not what ſhe look'd for, was always in a Melancholy Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and complain'd ſtill to her Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin of her bad Fortune. She ſometimes oblig'd her to keep her company the greateſt part of the day at the Window, where they could ſee all that paſt by, without being ſeen by any, flattering her ſelf, that ſhe might at laſt ſee him, who was now become the ſole object of her Thoughts. But notwithſtanding all this trouble for a whole month, it was to very little purpoſe, ſince that the <hi>Chevalier</hi> of—was now in <hi>France,</hi> where all his Eſtate and Fortune lay.</p>
            <p>The Count <hi>Centurione</hi> of <hi>Genoa,</hi> who had been acquainted with him in <hi>Italy,</hi> happening to be at <hi>Paris,</hi> after his return from a Voyage in <hi>Germany,</hi> was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd to find the <hi>Chevalier</hi> there. He went to ſee him, and was receiv'd with a great deal of kindneſs. It was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove two days after that the Count was in a troubleſome Affair with an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentleman. They fought, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentleman was much wounded; but the greateſt danger was, that they
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60133:15"/> were both ſeiz'd, and as none doubted but that it was a Duel, (which Crime in <hi>France</hi> finds no Favour) their Trial came on. The <hi>Chevalier,</hi> who was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertis'd of it, by a Note from <hi>Centuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one,</hi> took this Affair in hand, but fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing that they could not eſcape being convicted, and that his Friend thereby would run the hazard of loſing his Head, he thought it not convenient to endeavour any thing from the Judges, who, he knew, lay under indiſpenſable obligations of proceeding to give Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence according to Evidence; but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving underſtood, that they who ſaw the Action were People of a mean Quality, he privately ſearch'd them out, and by great Rewards oblig'd them to ſteal out of <hi>Paris,</hi> ſo that there might be none to witneſs againſt his Friend. This took the deſir'd effect, for the Judges finding no proof againſt him that was valid, were forc'd to acquit him. <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turione</hi> out of acknowledgment for this generous proceeding of his Friend, would have made him a conſiderable Preſent; but the <hi>Chevalier</hi> refus'd it, aſſuring him, that he was fully recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens'd for that care he took to bring his Affair to a happy end, by the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60133:15"/> he receiv'd in being ſerviceable to a perſon of his worth. The Count <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turione</hi> return'd back into his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try full of grateful Acknowledgments for the generous Action of his Deliverer, having always before his Eyes the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations that lay on him for ſo ſignal a piece of Service.</p>
            <p>In the mean while, the great Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe at <hi>Genoa,</hi> was of the Marriage of the Marqueſs <hi>Spinola</hi> with <hi>Peppa,</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing look'd upon as a thing agreed on between the two Families. The Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs <hi>Doria,</hi> who moſt paſſionately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd it, preſs'd ſeveral times her Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and her Husband, to procure a meeting of their Relations, to make an end of regulating all matters: But <hi>Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa,</hi> who was always full of the Idea of her Stranger, and who, not ſeeing which way to evade this Marriage, which ſhe now was afraid would be too certain, fell into a languiſhing illneſs, which equally put a ſtop to the Deſign of both Houſes; ſo that they deferr'd their meeting to ſeal the Articles to a longer time. The Phyſicians, tho they were ignorant of <hi>Peppa</hi>'s Diſtemper, preſcrib'd her ſeveral things, and through their Advice, ſhe was carried
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60133:16"/> to a Countrey-Houſe, which the Prince <hi>Doria</hi> had at <hi>Sancto P. di Arena,</hi> for a change of Air. <hi>Julia,</hi> who alone could adminiſter any Comfort to her, becauſe ſhe knew her Secrets, did in vain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent, that ſhe fill'd her Thoughts with the Idea of a Man, whom proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſhe ſhould never ſee again, and blam'd her infinitely for reſiſting her Father's Will, who would make ſure to her his whole Eſtate, upon her Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age with the Marqueſs <hi>Spinola. Peppa</hi> reſted ſatisfy'd with the Reaſons al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd by her Couſin; but at the ſame time affirm'd, That 'twas impoſſible to alter her Mind, and to drive from her Thoughts the Image of her dear Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
            <p>The illneſs of <hi>Peppa</hi> caus'd ſo much trouble in the Mind of the Marqueſs <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nola,</hi> who now really lov'd her, that his Relations thought it ſit to diſſipate his too great care for his Miſtreſs, that he ſhould go and ſee moſt of the chief Towns that were in <hi>Italy.</hi> Of this <hi>Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa</hi> was ſoon inform'd: And as it would prolong the Marriage, it became a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of great Conſolation, and from that moment ſhe grew better, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſhake off her Diſtemper: <hi>Julia</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:60133:16"/> forgot nothing that might divert her, and perceiving that ſhe did not ſpeak ſo often to her of her Stranger, there having been almoſt two years gone without hearing any news of him, ſhe inſtantly begg'd, that now ſhe would baniſh from her Mind, that fatal Idea, and conſider, that the happineſs of her Perſon, and of two Illuſtrious Houſes depended ſolely upon her own Will, ſince it was in her power to be the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieſt perſon in <hi>Italy,</hi> and to taſte the greateſt Delights that any rational Creature can here either expect or hope for. <hi>Peppa</hi> anſwer'd not a word to this Diſcourſe, which <hi>Julia</hi> took as a good Omen; judging by her ſilence, that by little and little ſhe would yield to Reaſon: Her Health, which daily augmented, fortify'd her Opinion, that the Stranger did not now ſo much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet her.</p>
            <p>The Marqueſs <hi>Spinola</hi> was at <hi>Rome</hi> when he heard that his Miſtreſs was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly recover'd of her Indiſpoſition. So good News exciting his Paſſion, through the Impatience it caus'd in him of ſeeing this charming Perſon, he thought of nothing but to diſpatch his Voyage to <hi>Genoa:</hi> And having heard
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60133:17"/> that at <hi>Civita Vecchia,</hi> there was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Squadron of <hi>French</hi> Ships ready to Sa<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> which were to put in at <hi>Genoa,</hi> he pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently left <hi>Rome,</hi> in company of two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gentlemen of <hi>Genoa,</hi> who were glad to take the ſame opportunity, for to return to their own Country. They arriv'd at <hi>Civita Vecchia</hi> the ſame day that the <hi>French</hi> Ships were to depart. The <hi>Chevalier</hi> of—that commanded the whole Squadron, receiv'd them with a great deal of Civility, taking them aboard his own Ship. As he had not been ignorant of the Name, and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Marqueſs <hi>Spinola,</hi> he treated him with a ſingular Reſpect. His Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, tho ſerv'd with all ſorts of deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates, was the leaſt of the Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. They often drank the health of Ladies, which oblig'd the Gentlemen of <hi>Genoa</hi> to tell the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> that the Marqueſs had a Miſtreſs, who was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the fineſt perſon in <hi>Italy.</hi> The <hi>Chevalier</hi> infinitely commended the Beauty of the Ladies in their Country, and confeſs'd, That being at <hi>Genoa</hi> in the time of the <hi>Carnaval,</hi> he went in Maſquerade to a Ball, whereof he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to them the particulars; but that he never was in his life in ſo great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60133:17"/> of taking leave of his Liberty, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he was forc'd to ſummon all his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſon, to reſiſt a ſecret inclination for <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ery amiable perſon that he had ſeen at a Ball, whoſe Name he nevertheleſs had not enquir'd after. He now thought certainly, that he ſhould never be in love, ſince that he had eſcap'd ſo great a danger. After this Diſcourſe the <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier</hi> drank the Health of the Marqueſs's Miſtreſs, and to do him the greateſt Honour that could be done at Sea, he fir'd all the Guns of his Ship. The Marqueſs, overjoy'd, told him, Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Miſtreſs was not unworthy of this Honour, and promis'd him, that he ſhould ſee her as ſoon as they came to <hi>Genoa,</hi> where they arriv'd ſoon after.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peppa</hi> was overperſwaded by <hi>Julia</hi> to receive favourably the Marqueſs, altho ſhe deſign'd to defer her Marriage as long as ſhe could. As ſoon as the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs was arriv'd, he went to wait on the Princeſs <hi>Doria</hi> his Aunt, who was not a little glad of his return. She carried him into the Appartment of <hi>Peppa,</hi> who anſwer'd him with expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons more of Compliment than Love, to all the obliging things he ſaid to her. After ſeveral Civilities paſs'd,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60133:18"/> the Marqueſs let them know the great obligations he had receiv'd from the <hi>Chevalier</hi> of—when he was aboard his Ship, with all the marks of Reſpects that he could wiſh, ſo far as to fire eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Gun of his Veſſel at the drinking the Health of the fair <hi>Peppa.</hi> He then gave them a very advantageous deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Perſon and his good Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and ſeeing that this recital diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleas'd not the Ladies, he inform'd them of the Adventure that happen'd to the <hi>Chevalier</hi> in his Maſquerade, and how far he forc'd his Inclination to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend himſelf from being in Love with a lovely Perſon, that he had ſeen at a Ball. <hi>Peppa,</hi> who at firſt found that the Deſcription of the <hi>Chevalier</hi> was very like that of her Stranger, remain'd much diſturb'd all the time that the Marqueſs was ſpeaking of what had paſs'd at the Ball, and of all the other Circumſtances which ſo exactly reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bl'd her Adventure, that the Company might eaſily have perceiv'd the diſorder that ſhe was in, if at the ſame time, the Marqueſs had not turn'd about to ſpeak to his Aunt in private, for to entreat her to find ſome means to make good his Promiſe which he had made to ſhew
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60133:18"/> the <hi>Chevalier</hi> his Miſtreſs The Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, who had a great deal of kindneſs for her Nephew, took it upon her ſelf to obtain her Husband's Conſent; and to accompliſh the better her deſign, ſhe told the Marqueſs, that ſhe would have on the morrow, at her Houſe, a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort of Muſick with a Collation, to which ſhe would invite the Ladies of the Neighbourhood, and that he might bring with him his Friend. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs retir'd well ſatisfy'd with the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient that his Aunt had found out, and did not in the leaſt perceive the perplexity wherewith the Mind of his Miſtreſs was agitated. As ſoon as he was gone, <hi>Peppa</hi> gave an account to her Couſin of all that ſhe had learnt; and as her Father had an eſteem always for the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and therefore ſhe being educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all along with Sentiments of Averſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for the <hi>French,</hi> ſhe ſhew'd no little trouble that this Gentleman, whom ſhe had found ſo agreeable, was a <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Julia</hi> acquieſc'd in her Opinion, and added ſeveral ſtrong Arguments to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade her from thinking any more of him. <hi>Peppa</hi> promis'd to follow her Counſel; but ſhe conjur'd her once more to lend her Aſſiſtance to find ſome way
<pb facs="tcp:60133:19"/> whereby ſhe might ſee again that dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Gentleman, aſſuring her, that ſhe had no other deſign, but that of diſcovering, whether this was the Stranger that caus'd all her diſquiet. <hi>Julia</hi> full of tenderneſs for <hi>Peppa,</hi> and altogether as curious, promis'd to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute her utmoſt to ſatisfy her in this point. They were both buſying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to find out ſome means to ſee this <hi>Chevalier,</hi> without being ſeen by him, when the Princeſs <hi>Doria</hi> entring the Chamber where they were, told them, That the next day ſhe would give them a Conſort of Muſick with a Collation, and that ſhe would invite ſome Ladies, whom ſhe nam'd to them. She advis'd them to dreſs themſelves with all the advantage they could, <hi>For may be,</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>the Marqueſs</hi> Spinola <hi>will bring ſome</hi> French <hi>Gentlemen, that came from</hi> Rome <hi>with him. Peppa,</hi> o'rejoy'd that Fortune offer'd ſo happy an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, whereby ſhe might ſatisfy her Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity, ſpent all the night with much impatience. She therefore retir'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to her Chamber, and went to bed ſooner than her uſual hour, as if that would haſten forward the night, and occaſion a quicker return of the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60133:19"/> Nevertheleſs ſhe found the time very long, and was not a little uneaſie in her thoughts. One while ſhe pleas'd her ſelf to think, that ſhe ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template, at leiſure, that dear Object, which before ſhe had ſeen but a moment, and which had made ſo great an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion in her Mind: Then again, ſhe was afraid to ſee him, and repreſented to her ſelf, a train of inevitable Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes, that would be the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of her reſiſting the Will of her Parents. In ſpight of all theſe Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the fear of being deceiv'd in her hopes, caus'd her greateſt trouble; for when ſhe began to think that the <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier</hi> of—might not be the Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that ſhe look'd for, and that all her aſſurance for it, was but the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port that ſhe had receiv'd of the Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> which ſeem'd to be like that of her Stranger; ſhe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore would willingly ſee him without running any hazard. In this incerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, ſhe took a great deal of care the next day to dreſs her ſelf with all the advantage ſhe could, and ſhe did not fail in her deſign; for the Princeſs <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> and <hi>Julia</hi> agreed, that they never ſaw her in a Dreſs ſo magnificent as ſhe was then. The Princeſs being perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60133:20"/> that ſhe did it to pleaſe the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs, appear'd extreamly ſatisfy'd. It is certain, that the richneſs of her Dreſs gave ſo much Luſtre to her natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Beauty, that all thoſe who ſaw her, could not forbear crying out, That <hi>they had never ſeen ſo fair a Creature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Marqueſs and the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with ſeveral of their Friends, came to the Conſort. As ſoon as they were enter'd into the Ladies Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>Peppa,</hi> who eaſily ſingl'd out the <hi>Chevalier</hi> from the reſt, was in a great Confuſion. She found, however, ſuch infinite ſatisfaction in ſeeing him again, that ſhe forgot thoſe Reflections which ſhe lately made. The Marqueſs pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented his Friend to the Princeſs <hi>Doria,</hi> who receiv'd him with much Civility. They then offer'd their Reſpects to <hi>Peppa,</hi> who had ſcarce the Courage to look up. The Marqueſs tranſported with Joy, ſeeing the great ſplendour of her Beauty, could not hold from ſaying to the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> That <hi>now he might judge, whether ſhe did not merit the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour he did her, when he drank her Health at the report of all the Guns of his Ship.</hi> The <hi>Chevalier,</hi> who immediately knew her to be the ſame perſon that appear'd
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60133:20"/> ſo beautiful at the Ball two years before, was in ſo great a ſurpriſe, and beheld her ſo attentively, that he gave no An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to what the Marqueſs ſaid to him. This Affection which coſt him a great deal of trouble to overcome the firſt time that he had ſeen <hi>Peppa,</hi> was now renew'd; and he found by ſome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate motions of his Heart, that it would be impoſſible for him to reſiſt. <hi>Peppa,</hi> who ſat next to <hi>Julia,</hi> had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways her Eyes fix'd on the <hi>Chevalier:</hi> She found him ſo much to her liking, that far from repenting of thoſe amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Sentiments ſhe had for him whilſt he was yet unknown to her; ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd her Couſin for her having ſo often blam'd this Amour; and ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to make her obſerve in his perſon, the new Agreement that ſhe each moment diſcover'd. The Marqueſs, who was wholly taken up with the Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, liſten'd to it with ſo much atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that he did not perceive the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion the <hi>Chevalier</hi> was in, and he flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd himſelf with the imagination, that his own preſence might in ſome meaſure be the cauſe of the Joy which added ſo great a Luſtre to <hi>Peppa</hi>'s Beauty. As the <hi>Chevalier</hi> ſpoke nothing to him in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60133:21"/> praiſe of the Muſick; he ask'd him if he did not like it? The <hi>Chevalier</hi> anſwer'd him freely, That <hi>altho he was always a great admirer of Muſick, yet he had not any reliſh for it now, when he had before his Eyes the moſt beautiful perſon of the World.</hi> The Marqueſs perceiving well that <hi>Peppa</hi> had the greateſt ſhare in his Anſwer, aſſur'd his Friend, That the Cuſtom of <hi>Italy</hi> could permit of a familiar Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, he would alſo be ſatisfy'd, that her Wit was no ways inferiour to her Beauty. The Collation being ſerv'd up, the Marqueſs pray'd the Princeſs <hi>Doria</hi> to place the <hi>Chevalier</hi> next to <hi>Peppa,</hi> to which the Princeſs eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcended, to pleaſe her Nephew. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho <hi>Peppa</hi> and the <hi>Chevalier</hi> had a ſenſible delight to ſee themſelves ſo near together, yet they were uneaſie in being depriv'd of the pleaſure of beholding one another; but the <hi>Chevalier</hi> not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willing to loſe ſo happy an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, found means to ſpeak to <hi>Peppa,</hi> without being overheard by any of the Company, That he ſaw it was impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for a perſon to withſtand his Deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; and as for him, he never would complain of his, for he was ſenſible, that he was born to adore her all his life.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60133:21"/> The Modeſty of <hi>Peppa</hi> would not allow her to give him an Anſwer to theſe Expreſſions, nevertheleſs ſomething in her Actions let him know, that ſhe was not diſpleas'd with what he had ſaid. The <hi>Chevalier</hi> ſatisfy'd with the progreſs he had made in his Amour, enter'd into Converſation with the other Ladies, and took care to ſay nothing afterwards but what every one might hear. The Banquet was concluded with much Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence; al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ho the <hi>Chevalier</hi> did not believe it had laſted long enough, yet before he retir'd, he had the pleaſure to meet the kind looks of his Miſtreſs, and by this mute Language of their Eyes, they fully diſcover'd the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they had for each other.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Chevalier</hi> ſpent the night with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſleeping; the lovely <hi>Peppa</hi> appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing always in his Thoughts, and he thought himſelf the moſt happy Man in the World, when that he repaſs'd over in his Mind, that ſhe had heard him without being diſpleas'd at it, that even her Eyes had let him underſtand, that ſhe had not an indifferent Affection for him; but preſently making Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon the ſtate of his own Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, foreſaw, that being advanc'd in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60133:22"/> the Service of his King, he could not receive into his Breaſt ſo great a Paſſion, and particularly at <hi>Genoa,</hi> without great hazard of ruining his Fortune. In ſpight of all theſe Reflections, his Amour got the Victory of all theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions, and he could not tell which way to take a Reſolution of parting from his Miſtreſs. An Order that he receiv'd upon his Arrival at <hi>Genoa</hi> to depart immediately for <hi>France,</hi> put him into the greateſt diſorder imaginable; but knowing how nice the King was in all that related to his Service, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd not to admit of the thoughts of deferring his Voyage one moment, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho he probably believ'd, that he ſhould never get ſuch another occaſion, or to agree with her what Methods and Meaſures to obſerve for the time to come. In this extremity he reſolv'd to write to her, for to let her underſtand, the real motions of his Heart: He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd it not till it was day; for having call'd his Servants, he ask'd for a light, and writ this following Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>I <hi>Once had the thoughts that I ſhould never be in Love, ſince I had the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to reſiſt its force, when I ſaw you two
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60133:22"/> years ago. I was confirm'd in this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion by infinite Arguments; but I had no ſooner ſeen you a ſecond time, when that all theſe Arguments, which before had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd to me invincible, became weak; and now far from endeavouring to preſerve my Liberty, I repent of my former Reſiſtance, and I eſteem the time paſt as loſt, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to comprehend, that there can be a Felicity in this World, equal to that of loving you. A Duty moſt cruel, but yet not to be diſpens'd with, obliges me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn ſuddenly into</hi> France. <hi>I ſhould have met with a far greater reſiſtance, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving this abſence, had I not believ'd, that that Man muſt be unworthy of you, who can fail in his Duty to his King. This reaſon alone makes me go without heſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating, but with a reſolution to make a ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy return, to find you out in what place ſoever you are; to adore you continually; and to ſacrifice my Life to a Love that is perfect, and conſtant.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>He found this Letter exactly confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to his Mind; but he was in a great perplexity, how to give it to the charming <hi>Peppa,</hi> for he very well knew, that the greateſt part of the Nobility of <hi>Genoa</hi> live extreamly retir'd, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60133:23"/> that it would be very difficult to have acceſs into their Houſes, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, near their Wives or Daughters. He fear'd, that if he ſhould commit this Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret to Mercinary Perſons, they would act but faintly in his Affair; and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in his abſence. He was thus diſquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelf, when that the Count <hi>Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rione</hi> enter'd his Chamber; he began to chide him for his unkindneſs, that he came not to lodge in his Palace. The <hi>Chevalier</hi> excus'd himſelf upon his ſhort ſtay, having an Order to make Sail from <hi>Genoa</hi> with all expedition. The Count perceiving him to be very unea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, conjur'd him to let him know, whether he could contribute any thing to his ſatisfaction; aſſuring him, that he would expoſe both his Life and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune in his Service. The <hi>Chevalier,</hi> ſighing, confeſs'd, That he had plung'd himſelf in the moſt cruel Affair that he ever met with in all his Life: This oblig'd the Count to renew the offer which he had made him before, add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all that he could think of, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him, that he ſhould eſteem him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the moſt happy man in the World, if he could find an occaſion to teſtify to him his Acknowledgment. The
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60133:23"/> 
               <hi>Chevalier</hi> without any further difficulty, made him a Confident in his Secret. Having in ſhort acquainted him with the beginning of his Adventure, he confeſs'd, that he was in Love; and that notwithſtanding he could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent his departing, and abſenting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from the only perſon he could love. The Count repreſented to him, the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt invincible difficulties that he would meet with in his Enterpriſe; but however he offer'd him all the Aſſiſtance in the World; and aſſur'd him, that he would ſtick at nothing where his Service was in Queſtion. The <hi>Chevalier</hi> ſhew'd him then the Letter which he had writ, and told him, That he ſhould depart with leſs trouble, if he would take the charge upon him, to convey it to <hi>Peppa.</hi> The Count ingag'd himſelf with a great deal of Joy, and promis'd to take ſuch exact Meaſures, that he might rely upon the ſafe conveyance of his Letter to his Miſtreſs. They had ſome other Converſation together be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Chevalier</hi> embark'd, to whom it was a matter of great Conſolation to find a Friend ſo truly grateful.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peppa</hi> paſt the night with as little reſt as the <hi>Chevalier:</hi> She would ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60133:24"/> ſtart as ſhe began to cloſe her Eyes, and then would imagin, that all which had paſs'd the day before, was but a Dream; but when ſhe recollected her ſelf, how that ſhe had ſeen diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> and that he had alſo ſpoke to her in ſuch tender Expreſſions; ſhe found no little delight in repaſſing in her Mind, thoſe very words he had us'd; and baniſh'd all Reflections that might diminiſh her Joy. As ſoon as it was day ſhe went into <hi>Julia</hi>'s Chamber, whom ſhe awak'd, to talk of her Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. She made her take notice how much Wit was in all his Diſcourſe, and even applauded his Diſcretion, for his having ſpoke ſo little to her in private. <hi>Julia,</hi> either to do Juſtice to the <hi>Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier,</hi> or out of Complaiſance for her Couſin, own'd, that if a weakneſs of this nature might be pardonable in a young Maid, ſhe was far leſs criminal than another, ſince the <hi>Chevalier</hi> in all his Actions appear'd ſo graceful. After a long Diſcourſe, <hi>Peppa,</hi> who flatter'd her ſelf, that Love might ſtill procure ſome new means for her to ſee him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, took no little care in adorning her ſelf. She was all the day long mightily diſcompos'd, and, under
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:60133:24"/> ſome pretext or other, viſited the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conies, and all the Windows of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace <hi>Doria.</hi> She was in this diligent ſearch, when ſhe heard the ſound of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral great Guns, which mov'd her Curioſity to enquire into the Reaſons: And being told, that the Gallies of the Republick ſaluted the <hi>French</hi> Ships which were under Sail. This news much ſurpris'd her, becauſe ſhe could not have imagin'd, that the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> after the declaring himſelf to her as he had done, was capable of departing, without letting her hear from him. She was ſenſibly touch'd with this appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Contempt, and call'd to her Remembrance all that ſhe had heard re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to the diſadvantage of the <hi>French</hi> Nation, who had this general Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter in their Neighbouring Countries, that they could eaſily ingage themſelves in any Amour, and as eaſily quit it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, without the leaſt concern in the World. She bemoan'd her misfortune to <hi>Julia,</hi> and in the angry humour ſhe was in, endeavouring to leſſen all that was charming in the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> ſhe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd her never to think more of this Ingrate.</p>
            <p>We muſt now leave the <hi>Chevalier</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:60133:25"/> purſuing his Voyage to <hi>France</hi> in a ſtormy ſeaſon of the year, and upon an unruly Sea; but whether that or his Paſſion was his greateſt care, this Song, the product of his ſolitary Thoughts, will beſt teſtifie. He ſent it with the firſt Ship, for his Friend <hi>Centurione</hi> at <hi>Genoa,</hi> who till a long time after, could not meet with an opportunity of putting it into the Hands of the fair <hi>Peppa.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="song">
               <body>
                  <lg n="1">
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> OH my <hi>Zelinda!</hi> could you ſee </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> the fury of each foaming Wave,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> you'd think, that the tempeſtuous Sea</l>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:60133:25"/>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> would e'ry moment be our Grave:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> But, oh <hi>Zelinda!</hi> could you view</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> the greater Tempeſt in my Heart,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> you'd know that it was rais'd for you;</l>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:60133:26"/>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> So ſad, ſo ſad 'tis to depart;</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſo ſad, ſo ſad 'tis to depart.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="2">
                     <head>2.</head>
                     <l>Come to my aid ſome gentle Wind,</l>
                     <l>And thus my Am'rous Meſſage bear;</l>
                     <l>Tell all the troubles of my Mind,</l>
                     <l>And whiſper how I love my Fair:</l>
                     <l>Tell her my Fancy all the day</l>
                     <l>Doth ſtill enjoy her glorious ſight;</l>
                     <l>But tell her too, that abſence may</l>
                     <l>Involve me in eternal Night.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Involve me,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:60133:26"/>
            <p>The Aſſembly of the Relations of both Families, which ſhould have met long before, upon the treaty of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage between the Marqueſs <hi>Spinola</hi> and <hi>Peppa,</hi> but which was then deferr'd by reaſon of <hi>Peppa</hi>'s illneſs, met two days after the <hi>Chevalier</hi> ſet Sail. They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated the Affairs on each ſide, and reſolv'd to have them married immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately. <hi>Peppa,</hi> who could not forget the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> in ſpight of all his Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, being inform'd of this Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, went preſently into the Chamber of her Couſin, where ſhe gave her ſelf wholly up to her Grief and Tears, without having the pow'r to utter one word. <hi>Julia</hi> did what ſhe could to comfort her, and advis'd her to obey willingly her Parents, and not to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard the Content of her whole life, by a vexatious oppoſition. She added, <hi>That it was part of her good Fortune to be undeceiv'd of the</hi> Chevalier, <hi>ſince ſhe had now found by her own Experience, that he never had a true kindneſs for her. I believe all that you ſay,</hi> interrupted <hi>Peppa, but yet you muſt acknowledge, that I am the moſt unhappy perſon that breaths, ſeeing that I am going to be ſacrifis'd to a Man that I can never love, when he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60133:27"/> whom I thought worthy of my Love, ſhuns me.</hi> The many ſighs and tears, which ſtifled her Voice, hinder'd her from proceeding any further in her Complaints.</p>
            <p>In the mean while that <hi>Julia,</hi> who ſhar'd in her Couſins ſorrow, lamented with her, the Count <hi>Centurione,</hi> who was to convey to <hi>Peppa</hi> the Letter gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> try'd all manner of ways to gain one of the Women that waited on her. After ſeveral In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treagues, finding that his endeavours to win her to him prov'd fruitleſs, he told her at laſt, as a ſecret, that ſhe might deliver it without the leaſt apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſince that this Letter came from the Marqueſs <hi>Spinola,</hi> who did only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to ſurprize his Miſtreſs, and to ſee if ſhe could gueſs whence it came. The Servant being overperſwaded by this falſe appearance, took charge of the Letter, and preſented it to her Lady. <hi>Peppa</hi> ſomething amaz'd at this novelty, demanded from whom ſhe receiv'd it. The Servant anſwer'd her, That ſhe was forbid to tell, but that ſhe would ſoon know in reading it. <hi>Peppa,</hi> who at firſt conſulted only her Honour, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd to receive it, but as ſoon as ſhe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:60133:27"/> was alone, ſhe repented that ſhe had let it go, imagining, that it might have come from the <hi>Chevalier.</hi> A hundred times was ſhe going to have ask'd her Servant for it, and as many times her Modeſty and her Fear, that it was the Marqueſs <hi>Spinola</hi> who had ſent it, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd her. In fine, after ſeveral Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, her Curioſity, or rather, her Love, got the victory. She ſent after the Servant, and threaten'd to turn her away, unleſs ſhe would declare from whence the Letter came. The Servant, ſtill reſerving that as a Myſtery, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd it without making her any An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. <hi>Peppa,</hi> for all her Modeſty, had not the power to reſiſt her Curioſity to know what was in it; ſhe read the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and immediately retir'd in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, to abandon her ſelf without any conſtraint, to all the tranſport of Joy that this pleaſant peruſal had caus'd in her. She read it a thouſand times, and a thouſand times ſhe repented of the diſadvantageous Opinion that ſhe had had of her Lover. Her Marriage, which was brought now to a concluſion, was a trouble to her not to be imagin'd. Her Love, notwithſtanding, gave her ſtill ſome hopes to find out a Pretext to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:60133:28"/> this Marriage: She reſolv'd, eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at laſt, to feign her ſelf ſick, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> make uſe of all her Addreſs, to preven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this Affair from being concluded. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the mean time ſhe buſied her Thoughts for an Anſwer to the <hi>Chevalier;</hi> which near upon was expreſs'd in theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>THE Rules of Modeſty would fearce permit me to anſwer a Letter that was ſo full of Gallantries as yours, but the ſame Deſtiny which has ingag'd you in an eſteem for me, does likewiſe compel me to do that for you alone, which I thought never to have done for any. I would therefore have you believe, That your Cares for me will not be unwelcome, and that I ſhall receive no ſmall delight when I may ſee you again.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Peppa,</hi> ſuppoſing that the <hi>Chevalier</hi> had found the ſafeſt way to hear from her, was content to take no further care, but only to remit this Anſwer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Hands of the Servant who gave her the Letter, not doubting but that ſhe would be faithful in the delivery; her Modeſty not permitting her to enquire into the meaſures that were to be taken. This Maid being prepoſſeſs'd, that the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60133:28"/> Count <hi>Centurione</hi> was of the Plot with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Marqueſs <hi>Spinola,</hi> and that the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wer which her Miſtreſs gave her was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eally for the Marqueſs, met him by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hance a moment after: She was ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leas'd with her Negotiation, that it was impoſſible for her to hide her Joy. <hi>You ſave me the trouble to go any further,</hi> ſaid ſhe to him, in giving him the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from <hi>Peppa.</hi> She withdrew without ſtaying for his Anſwer, for fear that ſhe ſhould be ſeen to talk with him. The Marqueſs, who knew the Hand of his Miſtreſs, taſted before-hand all the Pleaſure that a paſſionate Lover can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in having a Letter deliver'd to him from a perſon whom he entirely loves; but after that he had perceiv'd in reading it, that it was deſign'd for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and not for him, he was ſeiz'd with Horrour and Amazement, never having had the leaſt thoughts that <hi>Peppa</hi> was capable of a Love Entreague: His Indignation and Anger gave him not leiſure to make any further Reflections; he enter'd the Chamber of the Princeſs <hi>Doria</hi> full of grief, and giving her the Letter, utter'd a thouſand Reproaches, that ſhe would have had him marry'd a perſon who was ſo falſe to him. The
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60133:29"/> Princeſs ſurpris'd at this fury of he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Nephew, and the Expreſſions ſo littl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reſpectful which he us'd, read the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which he gave her. She ask'd the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Marqueſs, to whom this Letter wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> directed, and by what adventure it fe<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> into his Hands. <hi>I cannot ſatisfy you i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that,</hi> anſwer'd the Marqueſs, <hi>I know very well that</hi> Peppa <hi>preſerves all her Love for another, whilſt that I am going to marry her. It was one of her Women that gave me this Letter; you ſee hereby that ſhe was miſtaken, and it muſt be without doubt that ſhe was not well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed.</hi> The Princeſs made the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man be call'd, whom the Marqueſs had nam'd, and after having told her, that ſhe ſhould undergo the ſevereſt effects of her Anger, if ſhe did not declare the truth; ſhe aks'd her the meaning of this Letter. The Woman confeſs'd, That the Count <hi>Centurione</hi> had given her one to deliver to <hi>Peppa,</hi> that ſhe had acquitted her ſelf of the charge laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her, and had got an Anſwer, which ſhe put into the Hands of the Marqueſs <hi>Spinola,</hi> believing, as the Count <hi>Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rione</hi> had aſſur'd her, That they were both of Council together, and that it was all one to deliver the Letter to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:60133:29"/> either of them, ſince that the Count <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d no other deſign, but what was only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or the Intereſt of the Marqueſs. This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſwer made them believe, that the Woman had been deceiv'd. The Princeſs conjur'd her Nephew to have a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ittle Patience, and to let her have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ime to ſearch into the bottom of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntreague, aſſuring him, that ſhe would be the firſt that would break off his Marriage, if ſhe found that <hi>Peppa</hi> held the leaſt Correſpondance with the Count <hi>Centurione.</hi> The Marqueſs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, as well as he could, his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, promiſing, that he would pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently expect the event, and ſo retir'd. The Princeſs without loſing one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of time, ſecur'd firſt the Servant, ſhutting her up in a Chamber, whereof ſhe her ſelf kept the Key. She paſs'd from thence into the Apartment of her Daughter-in-law, and told her as ſoon as ſhe came in, That ſhe would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint her with ſuch News which would ſurprize her. <hi>Peppa</hi> was impatient till ſhe knew it. <hi>We have diſcover'd,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd the Princeſs, <hi>that the Marqueſs</hi> Spinola <hi>is ſo ſtrictly ingag'd with a Lady of</hi> Rome, <hi>that it is not in his power to marry any other, which makes your Father
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:60133:30"/> reſolve to hearken to the Count</hi> Cent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rione, <hi>who earneſtly demands you in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage: He gave me a charge that I ſhou<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> make you acquainted with his deſign, a<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to prepare you to receive kindly this n<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Lover, whom he himſelf will offer to yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to morrow. Peppa</hi> was wholly ſurpriz'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at this Diſcourſe which ſhe ſo littl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> expected. She conjur'd her Mother-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>law, with tears in her Eyes, to hinder the effects of ſo ſudden a Reſolution, telling her, That ſhe could not take up a Reſolution of marrying a Man whom ſhe had never ſeen, and hardly knew his Name. <hi>However,</hi> anſwer'd the Princeſs, <hi>your Father did not determine this Affair, but upon the conſideration that he was aſſur'd you have a great kindneſs for this Count. Peppa</hi> proteſted to her over again, That ſhe did not know him, and declar'd, that ſhe had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther live all her days in a Nunnery, than to conſent to ſuch a Marriage. <hi>I have never heard,</hi> anſwer'd the Princeſs, in a ſerious tone, <hi>that when one writes kind Letters to any perſon, they do not at the ſame time know who they are. Peppa</hi> touch'd with theſe laſt words, anſwer'd her coldly, That ſhe knew not what ſhe meant; and that without doubt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60133:30"/> ſome perſon, envious of her happineſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ade uſe of this Contrivance to ruin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er in the Opinion of all her Friends. The Princeſs ſaid, She was ſorry that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he muſt be forc'd to convince her; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd to let her ſee that ſhe had invented <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>othing of her own Head, told her, That ſhe need only follow her; ſhe brought her to the Chamber wherein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he had ſhut the Maid, whom ſhe call'd by her Name, as ſoon as ſhe had open'd the Door; but was mightily ſurpriz'd to find no body. This Maid frigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten'd by the threatnings of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, had found means to eſcape out by a private Door that was behind the Hangings, and ſhe left <hi>Genoa</hi> with ſo much Diligence and Caution, that it was impoſſible for the Princeſs to diſcover, whither ſhe was gone. <hi>Peppa,</hi> who was really innocent of any Intreague with the Count, but yet had fear'd the diſcovery of her Affair with the <hi>Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier,</hi> from the mouth of this Servant, became now more bold, by the abſence of the only perſon that could confront her, and reproach'd the Princeſs for her Injuſtice, in ſuſpecting her ſo light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The Princeſs touch'd with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches of her Daughter-in-law,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:60133:31"/> hop'd ſtill to convince her by the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that was in the Hands of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs, to whom ſhe writ, for to pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him to ſend it her; but it was in vai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for the Marqueſs, not being capable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> receiving Comfort for the Infidelity o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Miſtreſs, nor of pardoning th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Count <hi>Centurione</hi> the Artifice that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> us'd to make the Servant take charge o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Letter, reſolv'd to fight him; and having met him by chance the ſame day, he made him draw, after having torn in his preſence, <hi>Peppa</hi>'s Letter, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Count declar'd, that he was not his Rival, and that this Letter was not directed to him. They fought ſome time with an almoſt equal advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; but in fine, Fortune declar'd for <hi>Centurione,</hi> and <hi>Spinola</hi> was worſted. This Affair made great noiſe at <hi>Genoa;</hi> there was ſcarce a perſon but what talk'd of it, and ſtrove to ſearch into the Subject of their Quarrel. Theſe two Gentlemen, had nevertheleſs ſo much Diſcretion, that no body could diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, that the Daughter of the Prince <hi>Doria</hi> had any ſhare in the Action. The Princeſs inform'd of the Misfortune of her Nephew, and of the Declaration which <hi>Centurione</hi> had made to him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:60133:31"/> he would draw his Sword, began to believe that there was ſome Myſtery hid in this Affair, and that may be ſome perſon, who envy'd the Grandeur of the two Families, had us'd this perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtratagem to breed a Diſturbance, when they oblig'd the Servant to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver the Marqueſs this Letter of <hi>Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa</hi>'s, whoſe Hand without doubt they had counterfeited. All the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of this Intrigue, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, the flight of this Servant, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd her in theſe thoughts; and as one is apt to believe thoſe things which one wiſhes, ſhe reſted ſatisfy'd, that <hi>Peppa</hi> had been betray'd, and was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concil'd to her. The Princeſs was then willing to undeceive the Marqueſs; but whether that he was not ſo eaſie to be perſwaded as his Aunt, or that he was aſham'd of the advantage that <hi>Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rione</hi> had had over him, he went from <hi>Genoa</hi> without taking leave of any one, and paſs'd into the Emperours Army, which was then in it's March to raiſe the Siege of <hi>Vienna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſudden abſence of the Marqueſs <hi>Spinola</hi> ſurpris'd every body, and much troubl'd the Princeſs <hi>Doria,</hi> who here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſaw all her hopes fruſtrated, and the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60133:32"/> Union of the two Families as far off a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ever. Her Husband himſelf was muc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> offended at ſo extravagant a way o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> acting, and began to hearken favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to the Propoſals that one of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Friends made to him, which was to give his Daughter to the Marqueſs of <hi>Vill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mediana Celi,</hi> firſt Miniſter of <hi>Spain,</hi> and who ſerv'd at <hi>Milan,</hi> at the Head of a Regiment of Foot. He gave him for example, the Marqueſs of <hi>Los Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bazes,</hi> who went for one of the moſt cunning Polititians that had been in <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noa</hi> of a long time, who was more aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd of the Protection of <hi>Spain,</hi> by marrying his Children to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> than by his long Services. The Prince <hi>Doria</hi> was mov'd by theſe reaſons, and promis'd his Friend to conſider ſeriouſly of it. The Marqueſs of <hi>Villa Mediana</hi> having had notice of the favourable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination that the Prince <hi>Doria</hi> had for him, and finding that <hi>Peppa</hi> was one of the richeſt Heireſſes of <hi>Italy,</hi> came to <hi>Genoa</hi> in all diligence. The Prince <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> receiv'd him very civilly; which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd him to make uſe of all the Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries which were practis'd in <hi>Spain.</hi> He walk'd the greateſt part of the night under <hi>Peppa's</hi> Window, and in the day
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:60133:32"/> never fail'd to be at all the Churches that ſhe uſually went to; but <hi>Peppa,</hi> who ſtill flatter'd her ſelf with the thoughts of ſeeing quickly again the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> had the malice never to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard this diligence of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> who nevertheleſs did not diſpair, but hop'd that in the end his Conſtancy would prevail. In all his Serenades, Songs were not wanting, that declar'd the ſtrength of a Paſſion; like this that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="song">
               <body>
                  <lg n="1">
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> LOvely <hi>Coelia,</hi> let your Ear</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> liſten to my humble Pray'r;</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> let it hear your dying Lover;</l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:60133:33"/>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> let it hear, and then diſcover</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> how innocent, and free</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> I am from flattery.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> How little all! How little all the World I prize, </l>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:60133:33"/>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> to one kind glance from<hi>Coelia'</hi>s Eyes!</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> To one kind glance from <hi>Coelia'</hi>s Eyes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg n="2">
                     <head>2.</head>
                     <l>Welcome Shores to thoſe that are</l>
                     <l>Shipwrack'd, and of Life deſpair,</l>
                     <l>Or t'Offenders Pardon given.</l>
                     <l>Or to th' Holy Man his Heaven,</l>
                     <l>Not greater Pleaſures be,</l>
                     <l>Than <hi>Coelia</hi> kind to me.</l>
                     <l>So little all the World I prize,</l>
                     <l>To one kind glance from <hi>Coelia</hi>'s Eyes.</l>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:60133:34"/>
            <p>In the mean while that he forgot no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that would produce ſucceſs, the Marchioneſs <hi>Durazzo</hi> took her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter home, for to put her afterwards in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Nunnery, whereto ſhe was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd. <hi>Peppa,</hi> who had never hid any thing from her Couſin, and who found a great deal of Comfort in diſcloſing her Thoughts to her without any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, was ſo afflicted at this parting, that ſhe begg'd her Parents to let her be enter'd ſome time into the Nunnery where <hi>Julia</hi> went to take the Veil; but her Father would never conſent to it, which oblig'd her to lead a life ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry retir'd, ſcarce going out of her Chamber, and without any other Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure but what the hopes gave her of the return of her Lover. The Count <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turione</hi> had not fail'd to write to <hi>France,</hi> and to inform him of the Deſtiny of his Letter, and of all that had paſs'd at <hi>Genoa,</hi> ſince he was gone; and even gave him hopes, that if he would ſend another Letter, he would leave nothing untry'd that might procure him an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. The <hi>Chevalier</hi> ſent him a ſecond Letter, full of paſſionate expreſſions, which ſet his Thoughts on work, how
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:60133:34"/> to deliver it. The Zeal that he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or the Service of his Friend, ingag'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im to write with the moſt certain promiſes, that he would procure him greater ſucceſs in the delivery of this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Letter, than there was in that of the firſt. However, as he knew no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy that had acceſs near <hi>Peppa,</hi> and ſhe leading a life very retir'd, ſince her Couſin was not with her, it was impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for <hi>Centurione</hi> to convey his Friend's Letter to her. He inform'd himſelf of all thoſe who had acquaintance in the Palace <hi>Doria,</hi> if <hi>Peppa</hi> had not ſome particular Friends, whom ſhe lov'd to converſe with; he underſtood that ſhe lov'd <hi>Julia</hi> very well, and that ſhe would admit of no Comfort for her Abſence. The Count deſpairing of doing any thing for his Friend, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd himſelf every moment with his want of Induſtry, was afraid, that the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> who had truſted him with an Affair ſo delicate, might either have ſome belief that he kept Intelligence with his Rival; or, that he acted but weakly for his Intereſt, ſince that he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted himſelf no better in the charge he had undertaken, after he having en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60133:35"/> himſelf in the attempt, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd even a fortunate ſucceſs. The remembrance of the great Obligation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that he hath receiv'd from the <hi>Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier,</hi> and the generous means that he us'd in his Affair; this put him quite into deſpair. But when that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd, that the <hi>Chevalier</hi> might with the ſooneſt opportunity arrive at <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noa,</hi> and come ſecretly to his Houſe in hopes to hear ſome good news, and yet he had nothing to tell him: Thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> laſt thought put him into ſo great a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> confuſion, that he could with Pleaſure have quitted the beſt part of his Eſtate, to find an occaſion of being ſerviceable to his Friend, and to give him a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of his Acknowledgment. In this extremity, he took ſo extraordinary a Reſolution, that no example of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip can parallel. He had a particular acquaintance with the Marqueſs <hi>Duraz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zo,</hi> who was one of the chief Senators of <hi>Genoa.</hi> He one day made him a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, and after having declar'd to him in obliging expreſſions, the eſteem that he had for his perſon, he told him, That he ſhould be very glad to enter into the Alliance of a Man of his worth, and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:60133:35"/> to become his Son-in-law. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs, who knew very well the great Eſtate of <hi>Centurione,</hi> anſwer'd him, ſmiling, That his Daughters were not Fortunes for him, nor had that vanity to think of ſuch a Perſon as he was, who could make Pretenſions to any of the richeſt Fortunes of the City. <hi>Centurione</hi> reply'd, That he was not of the humour of the other <hi>Genoeſes,</hi> who in ſetling themſelves, minded leſs the ſatisfaction of their Minds, than procuring vaſt Eſtates; but that for him, he ſhould think him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf extreamly happy in marrying one his Daughters; aſſuring him, that no manner of Articles between them ſhould break off the Match. The Marqueſs charm'd with this noble Action of <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turione,</hi> told him, That two of his Daughter were already Nuns, that he had two others remaining at home, one whereof was brought up with the Daughter of the Prince <hi>Doria,</hi> and juſt upon taking the Veil; That if he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in the ſame Sentiments he already had declar'd, he might conſult with his Friends about it, and returning to him again, ſhould then be able to give him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> poſitive Anſwer. The Count retir'd
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:60133:36"/> very well ſatisfy'd; and as he was long before capable of governing himſelf and his Eſtate, it was not difficult for him to obtain the conſent of his Relations. The Marqueſs on his ſide, conſulted his Friends: His Wife, who perceiv'd that <hi>Julia</hi> had no great Inclination for the Cloiſter, was overjoy'd at the Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Count <hi>Centurione:</hi> She was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſcrupulous of putting her Daughter into a Nunnery againſt her Will, which made her perſwade her Husband to let her want no advantage, rather than loſe a Match ſo important. The Count <hi>Centurione,</hi> who in marrying <hi>Julia,</hi> was ſure of eaſily ſeeing <hi>Peppa,</hi> and of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing towards this fair perſon, the Pretenſions of his Friend, return'd to the Houſe of the Marqueſs <hi>Durazzo,</hi> and was receiv'd very favourably both by the Husband and Wife. The Affair being concluded the ſame day, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs preſented <hi>Centurione</hi> to his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and exhorted her in his preſence, to acknowledge all her life time, how much ſhe was oblig'd to the Count, who preferr'd her with a ſmall Fortune, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore divers Matches that would have been to him very advantageous. <hi>Julia,</hi> to whom ſuch a happineſs came unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:60133:36"/> eſpecially in a Country where the Eſtate regulates the Marriages, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd the Count with all the Marks of Eſteem, and acknowledgement that he could wiſh, and they were married a little while after with an equal ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction on both ſides. <hi>Peppa</hi> was at all the Ceremonies, and was ſo joyful for her Couſin's good Fortune, that ſhe gave infinite Praiſes to the Count, for the Generoſity that he ſhew'd. The Princeſs <hi>Doria</hi> who then thought ſhe ſaw further into this Buſineſs than the others, reſted ſatisfied that the Count had been of a long time in Love with <hi>Julia,</hi> and that the Letter which had caus'd ſo much Trouble to her Nephew, was the hand of this Kinſwoman, who writ much like <hi>Peppa,</hi> becauſe they had learnt of the ſame Maſter.</p>
            <p>The Count who ſaw <hi>Peppa</hi> every day, finding himſelf capable of ſerving his Friend, prepar'd a great Feaſt in his Palace, and did reſolve to take hold of this Opportunity for to ſpeak to this lovely Perſon in behalf of the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier, delivering into her hands the Letter whereof he had took Charge. And as he was infinitely contented with his Wife, and not enduring to hide any
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:60133:37"/> thing from her, he confeſs'd to her one day, after having aſſur'd her of his conſtant Love, that he eſteem'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the happieſt Man alive, in having married her; but that nevertheleſs he was beholden to one of his Friends for this great happineſs, who had rendred him the higheſt Obligation that ever Man receiv'd. He then told her, that this Friend was in Love with <hi>Peppa,</hi> and that he had ingag'd himſelf to ſpeak to her in his behalf; but that he reſolv'd not to attempt it without asking her Advice. <hi>Julia</hi> ſurpris'd at her Husband's Diſcourſe, counſel'd him forthwith, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndeceive his Friend, and told as a ſecret, that her Couſin was already ſo taken with a ſtranger, that tho' ſhe had made uſe of all her Intereſt to exclude his Memory from her Thoughts, ſhe found it was but to little purpoſe, and that her Couſin was reſolv'd never to forget him. <hi>You did then oppoſe the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of my Friend,</hi> interrupted the Count? <hi>I doubt very much,</hi> replyed Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, <hi>whether you know him that I mean.</hi> The <hi>Count</hi> was going to give her an Anſwer, when he was inform'd that two ſtrangers very earneſtly inquir'd for him. He went out to know what
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:60133:37"/> they deſir'd of him, and was ſometime without knowing who they were. He perceiv'd at laſt, that he whom he ſpoke to was the <hi>Chevalier</hi>—who was come to <hi>Genoa</hi> privately in a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe, and accompanied only with one Servant. The <hi>Count</hi> was overjoy'd to ſee him, and carried him into a ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Appartment, that he had already prepar'd for him, and where the <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier</hi> chang'd his Habit for that which was more ſuitable to his Quality. They had together a long Dîſcourſe. <hi>Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rione</hi> gave him an Account of all that had paſt at <hi>Genoa</hi> ſince his Abſence, and particularly of the Motifs of his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage. The <hi>Chevalier</hi> confounded with theſe extraordinary Obligations which he had receiv'd from his Friend, could not find words capable of expreſſing how ſenſible he was of ſo true a Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. The <hi>Count</hi> told him that this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day there was to be in his Palace a great Feaſt, the Order whereof the Princeſs <hi>Doria</hi> had taken upon her ſelf to regulate, and gave him alſo to underſtand, that perhaps he might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure him the Converſation of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs; but becauſe he had need of his Wifes help to ſucceed, he reſolv'd to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:60133:38"/> introduce the <hi>Chevalier</hi> into her Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence firſt, and thereupon he enter'd his Wifes Chamber, to prepare her for this Viſit. He inform'd her of the Arrival of his Friend; and after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving exaggerated to her the important ſervice that this Friend had render'd him, he prayed her to receive him with all imaginable kindneſs for his ſake. <hi>Julia</hi> who deſir'd nothing ſo much as to pleaſe her Husband, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd him to follow his Orders, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he aſſur'd him again, that the greateſt piece of Service, and of moſt Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage for his Friend, would be to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel him to think no more of her Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin. <hi>Let not that trouble you,</hi> anſwered the <hi>Count, may be that</hi> Peppa <hi>is not of your Mind.</hi> He went out without ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for her Anſwer, return'd a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment after, accompanied with the <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier. Julia,</hi> who knew him at firſt ſight, to be her Couſin's Lover, was in ſo great a ſurprize, that ſhe could ſcarce return the Civilities of the <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier,</hi> and complaining to her Husband, that he did not reveal to her his Friend's Name. <hi>Judge you,</hi> anſwered the <hi>Count, whether I had beſt counſel him to think no more of your Couſin?</hi> A Colour that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:60133:38"/> overſpread <hi>Julia</hi>'s Face, hinder'd her from replying. The reſt of their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe was of the Feaſt; They found it neceſſary that the <hi>Chevalier</hi> ſhould not appear; but that he ſhould remain hid in the <hi>Count</hi>'s Appartment.</p>
            <p>The Princeſs <hi>Doria</hi> and <hi>Peppa</hi> arriv'd ſome time after at the Count <hi>Centuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one</hi>'s Palace. The Feaſt was carried on with a great deal of Magnificence; and the Marqueſs of <hi>Villa Mediana,</hi> who would not loſe any Opportunity to be at all the Places where he might ſee <hi>Peppa,</hi> appear'd in a Mask followed by ſeveral Slaves, wearing about their Necks Collars, with a Motto in Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, which ſignifies in our Lauguage, <hi>Our Maſter has no more Liberty than we;</hi> but he was ſo little diſguis'd, that every one knew who he was. <hi>Peppa,</hi> who could no longer ſuffer the tireſome Gallantries of this Marqueſs, drew near to her Couſin, and told her, that ſhe had reſolv'd to come no more to theſe kind of Feaſts, that ſhe might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd from the Importunities of this Spaniard, who indeavour'd to infuſe Love into her Breaſt at a Time when ſhe had ſo much Reaſon to be afflicted, being ſeparated from her Lover, and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:60133:39"/> ſtill in an uncertainty of ſeeing him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. <hi>Julia</hi> promis'd her with an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent which ſhew'd the Aſtoniſhment ſhe was in at a Paſſion ſo conſtant, that if the Picture of the <hi>Chevalier</hi> could give her any Conſolation, ſhe would ſhew her one in her Husband's Cloſet, which repreſented him ſo lively, that ſhe would be ſurpris'd at it. <hi>Peppa,</hi> whoſe Curioſity was very great in any Thing that related to her Amour, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd her Couſin not to defer the giving her this Satisfaction, and of conduct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her to this Cloſet. They wanted not a pretence to get out from the Company, and went directly to the Count's Cloſet, where he was alone with the <hi>Chevalier.</hi> Never was any Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize more pleaſing than <hi>Peppa</hi>'s, when ſhe beheld her Lover. The <hi>Chevalier</hi> caſt himſelf at her Feet, and aſſur'd her, that he would now forget his paſt Misfortune, ſince he enjoy'd the pleaſure of ſeeing the Perſon that in the World was moſt dear to him. <hi>Peppa,</hi> who was unprepar'd for a happineſs ſo extraordinary, was at firſt in ſome Confuſion that her Lover ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs himſelf ſo paſſionately in the Preſence of <hi>Centurione;</hi> and ſeeking
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:60133:39"/> to ſave her Honour, which ſhe ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd this Interview might blemiſh, ſhe complain'd to her Couſin of the Cheat ſhe had impos'd on her. <hi>Julia</hi> preſently gueſſing the Cauſe of her Confuſion, told her that her Husband was infinitely oblig'd to the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> that they hid nothing from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that ſhe might declare her privateſt Thoughts before him without any Reſerve. <hi>Peppa</hi> taking Courage at this Diſcourſe of her Couſin, did no longer diſſemble the Joy that ſhe had of ſeeing the <hi>Chevalier.</hi> They diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd to each other all that had paſſed, and gave an interchangeable Account of all the diſturbances they had under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone ſince they had ſeen one another. Their Converſation had laſted much longer, if <hi>Julia,</hi> who fearing that the Princeſs <hi>Doria</hi> would be in ſearch for her Daughter, had not advis'd her to make haſte to return, for fear that ſhe deferr'd it too long, ſhe might be ſent for, whereby that which they deſign'd to keep ſecret, would be diſcover'd. <hi>Peppa</hi> being afraid leſt her Mother ſhould find her in this place, prepar'd to follow her Couſin's Advice, but ſhe made ſo little haſte, that <hi>Julia</hi> was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:60133:40"/> to take her by the hand, and carry her away almoſt by force. The Count ſeeing that the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> being depriv'd of what he lov'd, was in a condition which caus'd Pity, engag'd his Wife to make an Invitation for the next day, and directed her chiefly to get a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe from the Princeſs <hi>Doria,</hi> that ſhe would bring <hi>Peppa</hi> with her again. The hopes of ſeeing one another the next day, diminiſh'd the Sore that the two Lovers had to be ſeparated; and <hi>Julia</hi> accquitted her ſelf ſo well of the Commiſſion that her Husband gave her, that the Princeſs promis'd to leave her Daughter with her on the morrow all the day long. <hi>Peppa</hi> appear'd to be in a very good Humour during the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of the Feaſt. The Marqueſs of <hi>Villa Mediana,</hi> who expounded eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing to his Advantage, flatter'd himſelf that his Cares did not diſpleaſe her; and as he had never ſeen her ſo Handſome as ſhe was that day, he all along beheld her with a particular At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention. <hi>Peppa</hi> laugh'd to her ſelf at the vain Cares of the Marqueſs, and was ſometimes ſo malicious as to caſt a Look towards him, but after ſuch a manner as ſhould not give him cauſe to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:60133:40"/> have the leaſt Hope; however a <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard</hi> flatters himſelf much more than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Man, and particularly in Love. The Marqueſs of <hi>Villa Mediana</hi> ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd that he was no longer indifferent to <hi>Peppa.</hi> Upon this ground he writ to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Court, and let his Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions underſtand that he had the eſteem of <hi>Peppa,</hi> and that if the King of <hi>Spain</hi> would take notice of it to the Prince <hi>Doria,</hi> his Marriage would infallibly be accompliſh'd.</p>
            <p>In the mean while the Counteſs <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turione</hi> fail'd not to go the next day to the Palace <hi>Doria,</hi> for to deſire the Princeſs to keep the Promiſe which ſhe had made her. The Princeſs who was now very well ſatisfied with her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter's Conduct, and who endeavour'd to put out of her mind by all ſorts of Complaiſance, the injuſtice that ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd to have done her in ſuſpecting her of a Love-Intrigue, conſented without any difficulty, that the two Couſins ſhould go out together, and promis'd within a little while to come to them. The <hi>Chevalier</hi> who expected his Miſtreſs with the higheſt impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, was in extraordinary tranſports of Joy at her coming; and whether the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:60133:41"/> care ſhe had taken in her Dreſs, or t<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Pleaſure in beholding whom ſhe lov'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gave a new Luſtre to her Beauty, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fancy'd, that he had never ſeen her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> handſome before.</p>
            <p>Although their Diſcourſe was hel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the Preſence of the Count <hi>Centurion</hi> and his Wife, it was notwithſtanding intirely moving and paſſionate; and as the Buſineſs of the State did touc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> both their particular Intereſt, they alſo ſpoke of that. <hi>Peppa</hi> acknowledg'd to the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> that it was a trouble to her, to behold the Conduct of thoſe that govern'd the Republick, who took no care to put a ſtop to the Complaints that the King of <hi>France</hi> had made againſt them, whereof ſhe fear'd the Conſequence for the Intereſt of her Family, and for the further Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacle that it might occaſion to her own happineſs. The <hi>Chavalier</hi> aſſur'd her, that whilſt he was aſſur'd of her Love, the differences between the King and the Republick ſhould never give him any Trouble, ſince that there was not any probability that ſo many great Men, which, as he had heard, did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Senate of <hi>Genoa,</hi> could think to reſiſt a Monarch who had compell'd
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:60133:41"/> ſome of the greateſt Powers of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>pe</hi> to accept the Conditions of Peace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat he had offer'd them. <hi>Peppa,</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enturione</hi> approv'd of thoſe Reaſons, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd the <hi>Chevalier</hi> added, that after all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heſe beginnings of diſorder were over, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e flatter'd himſelf with the hopes that His Majeſty would give him leave to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eturn to <hi>Genoa,</hi> and to demand <hi>Peppa</hi> publickly of her Relations. This lovely Perſon ſigh'd at his Propoſal, and as ſhe knew that the <hi>Chevalier</hi> expos'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to all ſorts of dangers, ſhe conjur'd him to ſpare himſelf a little for her ſake, and to think how that ſhe ſhould never be comforted for his Loſs, and that therefore he ought to endeavour ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the Favour of a Perſon whoſe Life was wound up in his Deſtiny. So much goodneſs piercing the very Soul of the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> made him vow to her, that he was in diſpair to think of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; but nevertheleſs his Honour, his Duty, and the attendance that he ow'd to the King his Maſter, oblig'd him to depart inſtantly for <hi>Toulon,</hi> there to receive the neceſſary Orders from Court. <hi>Peppa</hi> did not diſapprove of his Reaſons; ſhe prayed him only that he would take all Opportunities to write to her, and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:60133:42"/> bid him remember that this would be the only Pleaſure ſhe ſhould receive in his Abſence. She could not utter theſe laſt words without melting into Tears, which ſo ſenſibly touch'd the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> that he was ready to dye with Grief at the feet of his Charming Miſtreſs. The Count and his Wife took care to ſeparate them before the Princeſs came, and were forc'd to deceive them both, for to prevent their Sorrow in taking leave of one another. They told the <hi>Chevalier</hi> that his Miſtreſs was return'd to her Father's, and aſſur'd <hi>Peppa</hi> that her Lover went away, that he might not be the cauſe of her relapſing into the like paſſionate Tenderneſs. And indeed he departed with his Friend, and return'd with the greateſt ſpeed poſſible into <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peppa</hi> remain'd ſo full of Grief for the departure of her Lover, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out liſtning to the Reaſons that her Couſin alledg'd, to oblige her to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the diſorder ſhe was in, for fear leſt the Princeſs <hi>Doria</hi> ſhould ſurprize her in this Condition, ſhe abandon'd he ſelf to her Grief, and was in Tears at the very moment that the Princeſs came. The Counteſs at firſt was in
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:60133:42"/> great confuſion, both for her Couſin and her ſelf; but ſhe ſupplied by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eadineſs of her Wit, the Indiſcretion of <hi>Peppa,</hi> for it coming into her mind <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o hide a little Dog, that her Couſin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ov'd very well, ſhe went to receive <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Princeſs in an Anti-Chamber, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>old her that he came in a good time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o comfort <hi>Peppa,</hi> who was in the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt affliction, becauſe ſhe had loſt her Dog. The Princeſs finding her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in Tears, told her that her Age did not admit of ſo much grief for the loſs of a Dog, and that it would not be difficult to procure another as hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome as that which occaſion'd thoſe Tears. The Counteſs aſſur'd her, that ſhe would ingage for the finding him again, but <hi>Peppa</hi> appear'd not the leſs afflicted, and went away a little while after with the Princeſs <hi>Doria.</hi> Howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver foreſeeing that her Couſin might perhaps ſend her Dog the next day, ſhe privately pray'd her before ſhe went out, to keep him at leaſt a Week, that the pretence of her Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row might remain, leſt otherwiſe the Truth might be ſuſpected.</p>
            <p>The Princeſs <hi>Doria,</hi> who had ſent a Man that ſhe could truſt into <hi>Germany,</hi>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:60133:43"/> for to inform her Nephew of the Coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Centurione</hi>'s Marriage, and for to clear all the doubts which might have ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd in his Mind, receiv'd, about the ſame time, a very obliging Letter from the Marqueſs, which return'd thanks for her kindneſs, and expreſs'd to her the great ſorrow that afflicted him for having diſpleas'd <hi>Peppa;</hi> he intreated further his Aunt to ſpeak in his Favour, and that he would expect an Anſwer at <hi>Venice,</hi> aſſuring her, that he would not go from thence till his Miſtreſs had pardon'd him. The Princeſs, who cunningly manag'd this Affair, waited for a favourable opportunity to ſhew her Daughter-in-law her Nephew's Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. In the mean time <hi>Don Carlos Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can,</hi> Envoy from <hi>Spain</hi> to the Republick of <hi>Genoa,</hi> went to the Prince <hi>Doria,</hi> as from the King his Maſter, to intimate to him, that this Monarch declar'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for the Intereſt of the Marqueſs of <hi>Villa Mediana;</hi> and that he could not by a more ſenſible mark, demonſtrate his good Affection towards the Court of <hi>Spain,</hi> than by receiving this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man for his Son-in-law; aſſuring him, that in favour of this Marriage, he would give him, when Opportunities
<pb facs="tcp:60133:43"/> did occur, all the marks of Eſteem that he could deſire. The Prince <hi>Doria</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, with a profound Reſpect, the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> did him, and aſſur'd <hi>Don Carlos Baçan,</hi> that he would immediately adviſe with his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily about it; and that he would ever obſerve that Submiſſion which was due to the Command of ſo great a Monarch. The Princeſs <hi>Doria</hi> was very much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm'd at this Negotiation; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſhe manag'd her Husband's Mind with ſo much Addreſs, and gave him ſuch good Reaſons, to let him ſee that the Marriage with the Marqueſs <hi>Spinola</hi> was a thouſand times more fit, and more advantageous for <hi>Peppa,</hi> than with a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> of whom they had no knowledge, either of his Eſtate or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, that at laſt the Prince <hi>Doria</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd ſatisfy'd, and promis'd his Wife never to conſent that his Daughter ſhould marry the Marqueſs of <hi>Villa Mediana.</hi> In the mean while, the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs <hi>Doria</hi> was reſolv'd not to defer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny longer the ſpeaking to <hi>Peppa</hi> in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of her Nephew, and ſhew'd her the Letter ſhe had receiv'd from him. <hi>Peppa,</hi> hiding part of her Reſentment, anſwer'd her coldly, That her Honour
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:60133:44"/> had been too ſenſibly touch'd to hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to a Man that had once no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eſteem'd her worthy of him. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Princeſs judging it not convenient t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> preſs her any further, imagining that ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhould find ſome means in length of tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to vanquiſh this nice Punctilio.</p>
            <p>As the Marqueſs of <hi>Villa Mediana</hi> ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> writ to <hi>Spain,</hi> that <hi>Peppa</hi> would not b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſorry to have him, and had the vanity to add ſeveral things to his advantage the Prince <hi>Doria</hi> near that time had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Letter from a <hi>Genoeſe</hi> that was hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Friend, who reſided at <hi>Madrid.</hi> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gave him an account, that he had heard talk of the offer that was made him to marry his Daughter to the Marqueſs of <hi>Villa Mediana,</hi> and how he alſo knew that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> us'd his Intereſt in the caſe; that thereupon he could not forbear counſelling him as a Friend, that if he aim'd at the Quiet and Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of his Family, he ought not to oppoſe this Marriage, being inform'd from good Hands, that the Marqueſs had before hand poſſeſs'd himſelf of the good liking of his Daughter, and that therefore he ought, as a wiſe man, to conſent handſomely to a thing that he could not eaſily hinder.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:60133:44"/>
            <p>The Prince <hi>Doria</hi> receiv'd this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with all the Regret and Deſpair of a Father, who has but one only Daughter, in whoſe Education he has taken great care, and who nevertheleſs diſpoſes of her ſelf without his ſhare in the Approbation. Not knowing where to lay the blame, he complain'd of his Misfortune to his Wife, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd her, in ſhewing her this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, with the Liberty that ſhe had given to his Daughter. The Princeſs had no longer occaſion of ſurprize at the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer that <hi>Peppa</hi> made her, when ſhe ſpoke to her of her Nephew. She advis'd her Husband to diſſemble his Anger, and cunningly to endeavour to procure from <hi>Peppa</hi> a Confeſſion of the Truth. <hi>Doria</hi> went directly into his Daughters Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and after he had exaggerated the Kindneſs that he had for her, the Care he had obſerv'd in her Education, and the Pains that he had taken, not only to conſerve the Inheritance of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but even to augment it; he told her that notwithſtanding ſuch manifeſt Obligations, he was inform'd from ſure hands, that ſhe had ſuffer'd her ſelf to be led away by the ſubtilty of a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. <hi>Peppa</hi> anſwering not a word to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:60133:45"/> this diſcourſe, her Father continu'd to exhort her to conceal nothing from him and promis'd her, that if ſhe did dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ingenuouſly, he would paſs by all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of complaint againſt her, and would let her ſee, that he was very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent. <hi>Peppa,</hi> ſoftned by theſe words and prepoſſeſs'd that her Father mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all this while the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> he being the ſole perſon that ſhe eſteem'd wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of her Love, thought that now ſhe would make good uſe of the favourable Diſpoſition wherein ſhe ſaw him, and caſting her ſelf at his Feet, her Eyes bath'd in Tears, ſhe confeſs'd, that it was true, ſhe did love. Her Father in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted her, without giving her the time to explain her ſelf any further, and after having reprov'd her with the higheſt Injuries and Reproaches, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd into his Wife's Chamber, for fear that in his Anger, he might be mov'd to any violent action againſt his Daughter. He was ſo tranſported with his Paſſion, and at the ſame time ſo penetrated with grief, that he fell dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly ill. All means were us'd for his Recovery, which being apply'd in time, did in a little while regain him his former health. His Wife, who every
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:60133:45"/> day ſaw him extreamly animated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Daughter, promis'd him, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f he would let her manage <hi>Peppa</hi> by a Contrivance to marry the Marqueſs <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nola,</hi> that ſhe would take ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act meaſures, that none ſhould know of it till 'twas done. <hi>Doria,</hi> not endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the thoughts that a <hi>Spaniard</hi> ſhould force himſelf into his Alliance, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Maſter of all his Fortune, in ſpight of his endeavours to the contrary, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd, that he would take no farther care what Son-in-law he had, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that <hi>Villa Mediana</hi> was not the Man. Soon after the Prince <hi>Doria</hi> being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly recover'd, his Wife, with his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate conſent, feign'd that ſhe had made a Vow to our Lady of <hi>Loretto</hi> for the recovery of her Husband, and declar'd that ſhe would go for to acquit her ſelf of it. <hi>Peppa,</hi> who was very glad of this Occaſion, to ſhew that ſhe was no leſs forward than the Princeſs in the care of her Father's Health, declar'd, that it would be a great ſatisfaction to her to accompany her in this Journey; and they ſet out ſo ſecretly, that only the Counteſs <hi>Centurione</hi> was advertis'd of their departure.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:60133:46"/>
            <p>The Princeſs <hi>Doria</hi> aſſur'd of her Husband's conſent, and prepoſſeſs'd that <hi>Peppa</hi> had not any natural Averſion againſt the Marqueſs <hi>Spinola,</hi> altho ſhe had ſtill obſerv'd ſome trouble in her Carriage, reſolv'd to finiſh cunningly the work that ſhe had begun ſo many years ago, and having ſent a Man in whom ſhe could confide, to her Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew, who was then at <hi>Venice,</hi> ſhe ſent him word, that it was time to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude an Affair that the two Families equally deſir'd; that therefore, as <hi>Peppa</hi> was one of the richeſt Heireſſes of <hi>Italy,</hi> and that new obſtacles might probably <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riſe to prevent his Marriage, ſhe had determin'd, thereby to avoid all Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies, to bring <hi>Peppa</hi> with her to <hi>Loretto,</hi> to the end, that he might ſeize upon her at their return along the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driatick-ſhore,</hi> where they muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity paſs. She added, that it being uſual to ſee Pirate-ſhips ſend their Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces aſhore, and take away by force whatſoever they meet with, ſhe judg'd it fit that he ſhould arm a little Frigat, and that he might not render himſelf odious to his Miſtreſs by this Violence, if he appear'd in it, he ſhould ſend a Pinnace a-ſhore with eight or ten of his
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:60133:46"/> Men cloath'd like <hi>Turks,</hi> who might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſet a little before day, a lone Houſe, where ſhe would lodge purpoſely; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat theſe Men, after having carried <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem away, and led them into their Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ace, ſhould take care to terrify them by all the appearances of a cruel Slave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and that the next morning betimes the Marqueſs ſhould purſue the Pinnace with his little Frigat, and after a ſhort engagement ſhould take it, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them: That if he executed all this with Judgment, <hi>Peppa,</hi> that was of the Humour of the greateſt part of young Ladies, who are always overjoy'd to have thoſe that court them, do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for them that is extraordinary, would be ſenſible of the Bravery that he might ſhew in relieving her, and would think her ſelf very happy to fall into his Hands, after having eſcap'd from thoſe of the <hi>Turks;</hi> that thereupon he ſhould conduct her to <hi>Venice,</hi> where ſhe would take care to have a Prieſt ready to marry them, whilſt the Impreſſion of the great Service he had done in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering her remain'd yet ſtrong in her Fancy.</p>
            <p>The Marqueſs receiv'd this Project with all the Joy imaginable, and as
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:60133:47"/> Time and the Advices which the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs had frequently given him, ſerv'd but to make him the more amorous, he prepar'd all things on his ſide to put in execution. The Princeſs always lodg'd at her return in ſmall ſtragling Inns, to bring her Project about. 'Twas in one of theſe Houſes, between <hi>Rimini</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cona,</hi> that the counterfeit <hi>Turks,</hi> ſent by the Marqueſs <hi>Spinola,</hi> put themſelves in a poſture to ſeize upon the Princeſs and <hi>Peppa,</hi> and to carry them off. They ſoon render'd themſelves Maſters of the great Gate of the Inn, and having ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify'd the Servants by ſome violent Actions at their firſt entrance, they run up into the Princeſſes Chamber, who had her Daughter in the ſame Room with her, and rudely forc'd them to dreſs themſelves with ſpeed. The Princeſs, who ſaw <hi>Peppa</hi> very much alarm'd, began to counterfeit a Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Mind, and exhorted her to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to her Deſtiny without murmuring, aſſuring her, (by a kind of a Prophetick Spirit) that Heaven would not aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don her.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Chevalier</hi> of—who was juſt upon going to take a great Voyage at Sea, was deſirous to take leave of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:60133:47"/> his Miſtreſs before he imbark'd. He went Poſt to <hi>Genoa,</hi> accompany'd with one of his Friends; having underſtood, when they arriv'd, that <hi>Peppa</hi> was gone to <hi>Loretto,</hi> he continu'd on his Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, with deſign to meet his Miſtreſs, ſince his time would not permit him to ſtay for her at <hi>Genoa.</hi> He happen'd to arrive very late at the Inn where <hi>Peppa</hi> lodg'd that ſame night that the Counterfeit <hi>Turks</hi> were executing the deſign of carrying her away. As this Project could not be put in execution without ſome noiſe, the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> and he that accompanied him, being awak'd out of their Sleep, ſtarted up, and quickly dreſſing themſelves, follow'd them ſo cloſe, that they came up with the Men juſt as they were preparing to carry off the Ladies on board of their Pinnace. They charg'd them with that Courage, that theſe ſuppos'd Pirates, who did not expect to find ſo fierce a Preventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, left the Princeſs and her Women, and retir'd in diſorder. However, notwithſtanding the Confuſion they were in, three of the ſtrongeſt, who probably knew their Maſters Secret, ſeiz'd <hi>Peppa,</hi> and fled in all haſte towards their Pinnace. The <hi>Chevalier</hi> having o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verheard
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:60133:48"/> her Voice, purſu'd them ſo hard, and with ſo much Courage, that he preſently diſabled two of them, and went to run his Sword through the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when that this wretch fell down, and begg'd him to ſpare his Life, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him, that he was no <hi>Turk,</hi> but that he and his Companions were em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd by the Marqueſs <hi>Spinola,</hi> who had agreed with the Princeſs <hi>Doria</hi> to ſteal away this fair perſon that he had now deliver'd. <hi>Peppa</hi> was ſo troubled, both with her Adventure, and with what ſhe heard this fellow relate, that ſhe ſcarce yet knew to whom ſhe was oblig'd for her Liberty. She juſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to thank her Deliverer in terms full of Eſteem and Acknowledgment, when ſhe diſcerned by the dawning of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay, that ſhe ſpoke to the <hi>Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier</hi> of—. Never in ſo ſmall a time was any one remov'd from a great Terrour into a perfect Joy. A mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment before ſhe thought her ſelf a Slave, and whilſt her Mind was ſtill poſſeſs'd with frightful Ideas, ſhe found her ſelf in the Arms of a Lover belov'd. So a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable a change is far more eaſie to imagin than to expreſs. The <hi>Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier</hi> related to <hi>Peppa,</hi> that he came to
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:60133:48"/> 
               <hi>Genoa</hi> with a deſign to ſee her, and that not having time to expect her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from <hi>Loretto,</hi> he had determin'd to meet her on the Road; that he arriv'd laſt night late in this Inn, where his good Fortune had conducted him ſo opportunely; thereupon he offer'd to carry her into <hi>France,</hi> to ſecure her from the Violence of her Relations. <hi>Peppa</hi> imagining at firſt, that the <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier</hi> ſpoke this only to prepare he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for a deſign of forcing her out of the Hands of her Father and Mother, let him underſtand, that her Father had ſome knowledge of his Paſſion, and told him, that ſhe did not deſpair of gaining at laſt his Conſent for their mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual happineſs; therefore ſhe conjur'd him not to deſtroy the Merit of the Service that he had now done her. The <hi>Chevalier,</hi> who of all Lovers was the moſt reſpectful, threw himſelf at her Feet, and complain'd of the mean Opinion ſhe had of him, aſſuring h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, that he would rather die a thouſand times, than to have the leaſt thought of diſpleaſing her. They continu'd, ſaying a thouſand kind and paſſionate things to one another, and gave new Aſſurances, that their Love ſhould laſt
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:60133:49"/> with their Lives. The <hi>Chevalier,</hi> who would not be known by the Princeſs; and who after he had broke her Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, would not have been very well receiv'd by her, deſir'd his Miſtreſs to permit him not to appear, and that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having conducted her ſafe to the Houſe where ſhe had lodg'd, he might remain undiſcover'd, and following her at ſome diſtance, might be her Guard till ſhe came to <hi>Genoa. Peppa</hi> acquieſc'd in his Sentiments, and in parting, when ſhe perceiv'd ſhe was juſt arriv'd at the Inn, ſhe pray'd him to remember, that working her ſafety, was employing himſelf for that perſon in the World who deſir'd moſt to compleat his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. The <hi>Chevalier</hi> had no ſooner left his Miſtreſs, but he met immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tely the Gentleman who had ſeconded him in attacking the Counterfeit <hi>Turks.</hi> This Gentleman, who had been trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled all this while for his abſence, told him, that he had been careful to attend the Princeſs <hi>Doria,</hi> and to prevent any ill uſuage that might have been offer'd her during this Confuſion, but ſhe ſhew'd ſo little Acknowledgment, that far from thanking him, her diſcourſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd full of Diſcontent, letting him
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:60133:49"/> know that ſhe was not at all oblig'd to him for his having expos'd his Life for her. This was no matter of ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe to the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> who preſently imparted to his Friend what he had diſcover'd concerning the private In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence that was between the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs and the Raviſners; and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe that he had made to this lovely Creature, to be always near, during the reſt of the way to <hi>Genoa,</hi> that he might be able to aſſiſt her, if there ſhould be made any further Attempt.</p>
            <p>In the mean while the Princeſs <hi>Doria,</hi> whom the <hi>Chevalier</hi>'s Friend carried back to the Inn, and who feign'd in the preſence of her Women to be much troubled, was comforted in her mind for the Misfortune which had happen'd to her Nephew's Men, being prepoſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as ſeveral Perſons had aſſur'd her, that they had carried <hi>Peppa</hi> off. She began already to think of going imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to <hi>Venice,</hi> to authoriſe the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of her Daughter-in-Law, by her Preſence, and by the Conſent of her Father, which ſhe had under his Hand, when that <hi>Peppa</hi> enter'd the Room. At firſt ſhe appear'd in a very great aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; but as Ladies, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:60133:50"/> thoſe in <hi>Italy,</hi> without any Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty at all can diſſemble their real Sentim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, the Princeſs threw her ſelf about her Daughters Neck, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly ſhew'd an extream Joy to ſee her eſcap'd from ſo great a danger. <hi>Peppa,</hi> who conceal'd alſo what ſhe had heard, and who was ſtill ſenſibly touch'd with what her Lover had juſt related, about his being forc'd to return imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately into <hi>France,</hi> embrac'd her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-in-Law, the Tears flowing from her Eyes. They preſently parted from hence, follow'd at ſome diſtance by the <hi>Chevalier</hi> and his Friend. While they were on their Journey to <hi>Genoa,</hi> the Marqueſs of <hi>Villa Mediana</hi> made uſe of all his induſtry to gain the Prince <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> over to his ſide. He engag'd his greateſt Friend to ſpeak to him in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of his Love, and made him ſee ſo many advantages for his Family, and chiefly for his own Perſon; that <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> was vex'd that he had given his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to his Wife, to marry his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Marqueſs <hi>Spinola;</hi> but when that he underſtood by a Letter from the Princeſs, the unfortunate ſucceſs of this Project, he thought that Heav'n would not permit this marriage, ſince it rais'd
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:60133:50"/> ſo many Difficulties, and now no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſcrupl'd to give <hi>Peppa</hi> to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs of <hi>Villa Mediana,</hi> eſpecially when he reflected upon the agreeable ſurprize this would be to his Daughter, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring to her ſuch News, as he did really believe would be pleaſing.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as the Princeſs and <hi>Peppa</hi> were return'd to <hi>Genoa,</hi> the <hi>Chevalier</hi> being oblig'd to be at <hi>Toulon</hi> before the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture of the <hi>Fleet,</hi> quitted this belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Place, without having ſo much time as to contrive an Enterview with his fair Miſtreſs. In the mean while the Marqueſs of <hi>Villa Mediana,</hi> who was ſatisfied of the good Intentions that the Prince <hi>Doria</hi> had for him, appear'd with a moſt magnificent Livery, and frequented all the Streets, and all Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where he believ'd he ſhould ſee <hi>Peppa.</hi> As ſhe was thus importun'd with his Services, ſhe took hold of all Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities to treat him ill, and was ſo malicious as to place her ſelf in the Church ſo, that the <hi>Spaniard</hi> could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſee her Face. The Princeſs <hi>Doria</hi> being inform'd by her Husband, of the Deſign that he had to marry <hi>Peppa</hi> to this Gentleman, obſerv'd ſeveral times, that her Daughter-in-Law was always
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:60133:51"/> careful to avoid him, and that ſhe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd to have an extream Averſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. She had much ado to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort her ſelf for not having ſucceeded in concluding the Marriage of her Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew, and this Deſign running in her Head, the leaſt matter rais'd her hopes. Therefore ſhe gave an Account to her Husband, that <hi>Peppa</hi> ſeem'd very far from having any Inclinations for the Marqueſs of <hi>Villa Mediana.</hi> The Prince <hi>Doria,</hi> prepoſſeſs'd (as he thought) with the contrary by the confeſſion of his Daughter, judg'd, as all Fathers are eaſily induc'd to flatter themſelves, that <hi>Peppa</hi> us'd this conſtraint becauſe ſhe would not diſpleaſe him. This ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd conſtraint ſo work'd upon him, that going thereupon to <hi>Peppa</hi>'s Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, he declar'd to her, that forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his own peculiar Intereſt, and not weighing what would be moſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous for his Family, he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd only of making her happy, and had determin'd in favour of the goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will that ſhe had for the Marqueſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Villa Mediana,</hi> to marry her to this <hi>Spaniard. Peppa</hi> remain'd ſo amaz'd at a Diſcourſe ſhe ſo little expected, that it was impoſſible for her to anſwer one
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:60133:51"/> Word. A Moment after ſhe fell in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>woon upon her Bed. The Prince <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia,</hi> ſurpriz'd and troubl'd at the ſwoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g of his Daughter, call'd for help; <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eppa</hi>'s Women ran in to her Aſſiſtance, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd the Princeſs came ſoon after. When <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e ſaw that ſhe was recover'd, ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eavour'd to conſole her by all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ays of flattering and careſſing, and at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ength demanded of her from whence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his Fainting did proceed. <hi>Peppa</hi> own'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat ſhe never had a ſtrong Averſion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut againſt one only perſon, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>evertheleſs ſhe was ſo unhappy, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er Father had made choice of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ery ſame Perſon to make his Son-in-Law. The Princeſs, after having aſſur'd her that the Prince <hi>Doria</hi> would not uſe ſuch Violence to her Affections, went towards her Husband, and blam'd him very much for having driven his Daughter into Deſpair, ſince that he might have remember'd, how ſhe had already perceiv'd that <hi>Peppa</hi> had no <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>clinations for <hi>Villa Mediana. Doria,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o comprehended nothing of all this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat he heard, believ'd that his Wife, who as ſhe was ingenious and contriving, had turn'd the Mind of his Daughter, and had ingag'd her to prefer the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:60133:52"/> 
               <hi>Spinola</hi> before the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> which confirm'd him in the Opinion that he had already of the Inconſtancy of the greateſt part of Women; but he was nevertheleſs in a great Perplexity and Doubt what meaſures to take.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, as the Senate did not proceed to any Reſolution to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the King of <hi>France,</hi> upon thoſe occaſions of Complaint that he had caus'd to be declar'd to the Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, the <hi>French</hi> Envoy retir'd from <hi>Genoa;</hi> which rais'd cruel Apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the Minds of the greateſt part of the Senators, eſpecially ſince they came to know that there was fitting out at <hi>Toulon</hi> a great Fleet, and that all the Ships were loaded with a prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious quantity of Bombs, Granadoes, and Mortar-pieces. The Commonalty maintain'd that all theſe great Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations were made againſt the <hi>Algereens,</hi> whom the <hi>French</hi> deſign'd to extermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate. The greateſt part of the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noeſes</hi> believ'd all this to be very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable; beſides they were ſo poſſeſſed, that it was a difficult matter for any State to injure them, that they would never believe that theſe forces were preparing againſt <hi>Genoa;</hi> but the wiſer
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:60133:52"/> ſort who know that Kings do ſeldom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et Affronts go unpuniſh'd, liv'd in great fears, and were of Opinion that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey ought to accommodate the matter with that King upon any Terms. The publick Affairs employ'd every Body <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o hard, and private perſons were ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſiduous at Council, and at the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent Aſſemblies that were thereupon ſummon'd, that none had leiſure to think of their domeſtick Affairs. The Prince <hi>Doria,</hi> who was without contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction one of the moſt conſiderable of the City, was call'd every moment to the Conſultation of the Senate, and the little Time that he had to himſelf, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd him to defer his private Affairs. He determin'd therefore, by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of his Wife, not to fix upon any Reſolution about the Marriage of his Daughter, while this Buſineſs which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd the publick was not fully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided.</p>
            <p>While the Affairs of <hi>Genoa</hi> were in this Condition, <hi>Peppa</hi> liv'd in continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al fears, encompaſs'd with her Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, under the Authority of a Father, who would ſacrifice her to a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and under a Mother-in-Law, who me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditated new Projects to betray her to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:60133:53"/> the Marqueſs <hi>Spinola.</hi> Every thing wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuſpected by her, and at laſt the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Calamity became her private con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation; for the formidable Fleet tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>French</hi> fitted out, and the juſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of Complaint that the King had againſt the <hi>Genoeſes,</hi> though a matter of diſquiet to all, was the only Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of her joy, and the only thing that nouriſh'd her Hopes, becauſe that if the <hi>French</hi> King became Maſter of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noa,</hi> ſhe ſhould then have the Pleaſure, by loving the <hi>Chevalier</hi> of—to be aſſur'd before-hand of a Powerful Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector for her Family. As ſhe could not find one Perſon but what ſpoke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>French,</hi> ſhe avoided all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation: Her Couſin to whom ſhe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clos'd her moſt ſecret thoughts, was the only Perſon that ſhe thought endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Reaſon, ſince ſhe condemn'd not the <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much about that time they heard that the <hi>Divan</hi> of <hi>Algiers,</hi> more cunning then the Senate of <hi>Genoa,</hi> had made his Peace with the King, without ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for new Marks of his Anger, and that he had already ſent away Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours, to ask this Monarch Pardon for what was paſt. This news put the
<pb facs="tcp:60133:53"/> 
               <hi>Genoeſes</hi> quite into Deſpair, no longer doubting but that the Storm which was gather'd about <hi>Toulon,</hi> would fall upon their City. The Senate aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at all Hours in the Day; at eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry turn they were making new Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, but never came to any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion. The Wiſeſt were of Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that it was beſt to ſend away Poſt an Embaſſador to make their Submiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the King; others judg'd that it was too late. The Envoy of <hi>Spain</hi> hereupon arriv'd, promis'd them that they ſhould not want a Fleet bravely mann'd, nor a Warlike Army: And he would ſend for all the Gold of <hi>Peru</hi> for their Service. Although their Counſels were very different, they receiv'd however a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment into the City, which the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Millan</hi> ſent thither. They alſo recall'd all the Bandits, and as much as the Confuſion (wherein they were) would permit them, they diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted through all Parts ſuch Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders as were neceſſary to put them in a Condition of making a vigorous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance. In the mean time the moſt conſiderable Perſons of the City, ſent their Wives and Children to <hi>Millan,</hi>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:60133:54"/> and to the other neighbouring Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. The Prince <hi>Doria,</hi> after having moſt tenderly embrac'd his Wife and his Daughter, would alſo have them take their Leave of <hi>Genoa,</hi> and gave them an Equipage more numerous than magnificent. He advis'd the Princeſs his Wife to retire either to <hi>Millan,</hi> or to <hi>Turin,</hi> which ſhe thought moſt convenient; and above all things recommended his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to her Care. The Princeſs <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> who had ſtill a deſign for her Nephew, and who fear'd the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Marqueſs of <hi>Villa Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diana,</hi> would not therefore go to <hi>Millan,</hi> leſt ſhe ſhould deliver her ſelf up into the Hands of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards.</hi> She retir'd to <hi>Turin,</hi> where ſhe had ſome Relations, believing as ſhe had Reaſon, that ſhe ſhould there have her Liberty more than at <hi>Millan.</hi> Soon after her Arrival, ſhe writ to the Marqueſs <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nola,</hi> who was ſtill at <hi>Venice,</hi> ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him Word that ſhe impatiently expected him.</p>
            <p>The Court of <hi>Savoy,</hi> which is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out contradiction one of the moſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite in all <hi>Europe,</hi> has been an inviola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:60133:54"/> Sanctuary for the Illuſtrious Unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate. It would be even a difficult matter to find a Stranger that was ever diſcontented with his Reception at <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin.</hi> The Officers of the <hi>Portugueſe</hi> Fleet can teſtify, whether <hi>Victor Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deus</hi> the Second, who now Reigns in-<hi>Savoy</hi> and <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>mont,</hi> has degenerated from the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cency of his Anceſtors; and of la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, the Officers of the King of <hi>France</hi>'s Houſhold, retir'd from <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay,</hi> loaden with Preſents, and ſo extreamly ſatisfy'd with their acting after an obliging manner, which doubl'd their value, that at their return, there was not one but what ſpoke the Elogies of the Duke of <hi>Savoy.</hi> This Prince had juſt eſpous'd <hi>Madamoiſelle,</hi> the Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of many Kings, and to ſpeak in a word, Daughter to <hi>Monſieur</hi> of <hi>France.</hi> Upon the Princeſs <hi>Doria</hi>'s ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving at <hi>Turin,</hi> the Duke, who knew her Merit and Quality, receiv'd her with all the marks of Eſteem that ſhe could wiſh or expect, and offer'd her very obligingly, all that was in his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. <hi>Peppa,</hi> who did not want the Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of her Birth, to gain the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects of all whereſoever ſhe appear'd, was regarded by all the Nobility with
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:60133:55"/> Admiration. The Ladies perhap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> could not ſee her without ſome Jealouſie, whereof there was no great cauſe of wonder. Nevertheleſs ſhe was not at any of the Diverſions that the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> had prepar'd at the arrival of the Dutcheſs, becauſe the Princeſs <hi>Doria</hi> pretended to a Preheminence which could not be granted her, without In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice to ſeveral Ladies of extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Quality, who were at the Court of <hi>Savoy.</hi> The Nobility, who would have been very glad to have ſeen <hi>Peppa</hi> at all the Entertainments, propos'd ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Expedients, to ſatisfy the Princeſs <hi>Doria;</hi> but as it is much more eaſie to regulate the Intereſts of Princes, than the Ranks of Ladies, they found it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to bring it to a Concluſion. The diſorder of the Affairs at <hi>Genoa</hi> ſerv'd well enough for a Pretence to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe her abſence from the Diverſions of the Court; for there came news, that the <hi>French</hi> Fleet was before <hi>Genoa,</hi> that ſeveral Voluntiers had landed, and that after having made themſelves Maſters of the Fort of St. <hi>Peter di Arena,</hi> they had burnt thoſe fine Country-Houſes which were the Delight of the <hi>Genoeſes;</hi> that the Frigats warping cloſe to the City,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:60133:55"/> had caſt into it ſuch a prodigious quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Bombs and Granado's, that it appear'd rather a <hi>Mount-Etna</hi> cover'd with Flames, than that <hi>Genoa</hi> which was nam'd <hi>Genoa la ſuperba;</hi> and in fine, that the Conſternation was ſo great, that ſeveral Families retir'd to the Mountains, and abandon'd both their Goods and their Houſes; eſteeming themſelves happy if they could ſecure their perſons ſafe, as well from the Fire, as from the Banditti, who began to pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage the City. There was added to all theſe Circumſtances, that the <hi>French</hi> had loſt ſeveral Voluntiers at their landing before the Fort of St. <hi>Peter di Arena,</hi> and that alſo a <hi>Chevalier</hi> of a very great worth, who was one of the moſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Officers of the Fleet had been kill'd upon the place; and that he was generally lamented by all the Army. All this news was a ſenſible affliction to the Princeſs <hi>Doria;</hi> but when that <hi>Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa</hi> was inform'd of the loſs that the <hi>French</hi> had receiv'd, and of the death of a <hi>Chevalier,</hi> who was a perſon very deſerving; her Love, which at this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port was allarm'd, made her tremble for the Life of her Lover, and all the Circumſtances that ſhe had heard of the Merit of this Chevalier, and of the
<pb facs="tcp:60133:56"/> ſorrow that every body ſhew'd for his loſs, encreas'd her Terrour. She pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately retir'd, and before-hand gave her ſelf wholly up to all the Emotions of Grief, which a perſon that loves ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly can be capable of at ſuch a time. She paſt over two whole days without mitigating in the leaſt her trouble: Her Grief oppreſs'd her in a very high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and altho ſhe had ſtill a ſmall ſpark of hopes left her, believing that there muſt be ſeveral Officers of Merit in ſo great a Fleet as this of the King's, ſhe durſt not however enquire of the Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of the News, fancying that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhe ſhould hear ſpoke of the <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier</hi> that was dead could be apply'd to none but her Lover. The Princeſs <hi>Doria,</hi> who would not be comforted for the Misfortunes wherewith her Country was oppreſs'd, had not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd the great Diſturbance that <hi>Peppa</hi> lay under. But ſeeing that ſhe came not out to receive the Ladies that viſited them, ſhe ſent to her to come into her Chamber for to hear the reading of a long News-Letter in the preſence of ſeveral perſons, giving an account of all that had paſs'd at <hi>Genoa.</hi> Although <hi>Peppa</hi> had reſolv'd to prefer the cruelleſt troubles wherein ſhe was, before the clearing
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:60133:56"/> her Doubts, which might prove either very Tragical, or elſe very pleaſing, yet ſhe could not reſiſt her timerous and preſſing Curioſity to be inform'd of the deſtiny of her Lover. She enter'd her Mother-in-laws Chamber, where ſhe found ſeveral Ladies who impatiently expected her, but rather for to know the particulars of the Affairs of <hi>Genoa.</hi> The Princeſs <hi>Doria</hi> read her Letter, which confirm'd all that ſhe had heard before at <hi>Turin.</hi> They ſent her word, after the ſeveral Circumſtances of the <hi>French</hi> landing, that they had loſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſpot, ſeveral Officers, and that above all, they were extreamly afflicted for the loſs of the <hi>Chevalier de Lhery,</hi> who was a Gentleman much eſteem'd, and who upon all occaſions had given proof of his Valour and Conduct. This name which ſounded like that of the <hi>Chevalier</hi> of—, whether or no it was ill ſpelt in the Letter, or that the Princeſs pronounc'd it not well in <hi>Italian,</hi> caſt <hi>Peppa</hi> into ſuch an exceſs of Grief, that it depriv'd her of her Senſes. She underſtood it to be the <hi>Chevalier</hi> of—, and at the ſame moment ſhe fainted away upon a Couch where ſhe ſat. The Ladies ran to her aſſiſtance, but had no ſuſpicion that the loſs of the
<pb facs="tcp:60133:57"/> 
               <hi>French</hi> was the cauſe of her fainting, being perſwaded that <hi>Peppa,</hi> touch'd with the Relation of ſo many Misfortunes, whereof the <hi>French</hi> Fleet had been the occaſion at <hi>Genoa,</hi> was thereupon ſeiz'd with this weakneſs. They had much ado to recover her, and were forc'd at laſt to call her Women to her, who having quickly undreſs'd her, put her to Bed. She was pierc'd to the Heart with this cruel News, and fell into ſo violent a diſorder, that ſhe ſpent ſeveral days with a careleſs Indifference for every thing, and almoſt without any viſible Senſe; and if there was ſometimes a ſmall interval from her exceſs of Grief, 'twas only to make her the more tormentingly ſenſible of her loſs. She reprov'd her ſelf, for her (as ſhe thought) Indifference, for having ſtill had the Courage to live, ſince ſhe could no longer doubt the death of her Lover; ſhe continu'd many days in theſe cruel ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, but at laſt, the force of her Youth ſurmounted ſo far that of her Grief, as to permit her, when ſhe had no Company in her Chamber, to paſs ſome melancholy moments in breathing forth this Song.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="song">
               <body>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> COme, come gentle Death, <pb n="101" facs="tcp:60133:57"/> and cloſe theſe Eyes; </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> come ſtop the Current of my Grief; </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> on you my Reſt relies,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> be quick with your Relief: </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> For by the chance of War my <hi>Damon'</hi>s laid, </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> mangl'd, and <pb n="102" facs="tcp:60133:58"/> bloody in his Grave:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> Oh God! Oh God of Battel! No diſtinction made</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> between the Coward, and the Brave! </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Zelinda</hi> weep, <hi>Zelinda</hi> weep, until thy Tears </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> drown both <pb n="103" facs="tcp:60133:58"/> thy ſelf, and all thy Cares;</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> but haſten ſooner, (oh ye Gods!) my Doom,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> that I may fly, that I may fly to <hi>Damon</hi> in his Tomb, </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="music">
                           <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                        </gap> to <hi>Da╌mon</hi> in his Tomb.</l>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:60133:59"/>
            <p>The Princeſs <hi>Doria,</hi> who daily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected her Nephew, whom ſhe knew was gone from <hi>Venice,</hi> left nothing untried to manage the Inclinations of <hi>Peppa,</hi> and although ſhe could not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the Reaſon of the Deſpair wherewith ſhe ſaw her oppreſs'd, ſhe notwithſtanding acted with all ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable Complaiſance. The Marqueſs <hi>Spinola,</hi> being arriv'd at <hi>Turin</hi> about this Time, went immediately to find his Aunt, who receiv'd him with inexpreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Joy; but ſhe durſt not preſent him to her Daughter-in-Law, in the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order wherein ſhe then was. However the next day after his Arrival, ſhe would carry him to ſee <hi>Peppa,</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinking her ſelf of the Anguiſh that afflicted her, ſhe deſir'd the Marqueſs to ſtay in the Anti-Chamber, whilſt ſhe would go and prepare her to receive him obligingly. She thereupon went into <hi>Peppa</hi>'s Chamber, and after having order'd the Women to withdraw that ſerv'd her, ſhe told her that the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>Spinola</hi> was juſt arriv'd, that he had paſs'd through <hi>Genoa,</hi> and that he could give a more particular account of every Accident that had happen'd there. <hi>Peppa,</hi> who preſently perceiv'd that the Princeſs aim'd at ſome new Deſign in
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:60133:59"/> favour of her Nephew, gave her not time to proceed, but interrupting her with Tears in her Eyes, told her that ſhe would now no longer make a Secret of her Inclinations which ſhe had hid till then, ſince alſo ſhe had now nothing more to truſt to, being reſolv'd to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive her ſelf of Worldly Converſe, which was become inſupportable to her. She then declar'd that ſhe had all along had ſome Inclination for the <hi>Chevalier</hi> of—ſince they ſaw one another at the Ball, that was given at the Palace of the Marqueſs <hi>Juſtiniani;</hi> that Sympathy had work'd the ſame Effect upon the mind of the <hi>Chevalier</hi> who retir'd into <hi>France,</hi> for to avoid the Conſequence of this Inclination, which forc'd him to love in ſpite of all his Reſolution; that they had run o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver two years without either ſeeing or knowing one another till the time that the Marqueſs <hi>Spinola</hi> being by chance return'd from <hi>Rome</hi> with the <hi>Chevalier</hi> of—had conducted him to their Houſe, and ſo had unknowingly given them the Opportunity to revive their firſt Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to declare a-new their Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to love with a Paſſion moſt violent and laſting; that in the end, their Love had taught them an Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:60133:60"/> both to ſee, and to Write to one another, as well as to exchange on both ſides an Aſſurance to continue firm in their Sentiments. <hi>'Twas he,</hi> added <hi>Peppa, that arriv'd ſo opportunely in the way to</hi> Loretto, <hi>as to deliver me from the Turks, who were not what they appear'd, for one of them confeſs'd to us, that they were employ'd by your Nephew, who had pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately agreed with you, to carry me off by force. I never yet ſpoke to you of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe being aſſur'd of the Conſtancy of my Lover, all other things gave me not the leaſt trouble. I ſtill flatter'd my ſelf with the Hopes that the Senate would make their Peace with the King of</hi> France, <hi>and that that might facilitate our Marriage; but all theſe flattering hopes are vaniſh'd, and I now propoſe to my ſelf no other Conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but that of lamenting the Loſs of my Lover, all the reſt of my Life.</hi> She pour'd forth a Flood of Tears, in uttering theſe laſt words. Nevertheleſs ſhe continu'd her Diſcourſe, and told the Princeſs that ſhe was reſolv'd to go throw her ſelf at the feet of the Dutcheſs, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat her Protection, and to beg that ſhe might be receiv'd into the Society of the Nuns of the Annunciation. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, if after the Confeſſion that ſhe had made, there remain'd yet in her Breaſt
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:60133:60"/> ſome Sentiments of Compaſſion for her, ſhe might if ſhe pleas'd eaſily ſave her the Confuſion that would ſeize her when ſhe went to inform ſo great a Princeſs of her weakneſs, and prevent her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming the talk of all the Court; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe expected this promiſe from her that ſhe might be conducted to this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent wherein ſhe deſir'd to enter without ſtaying for her Father's Orders. The Princeſs melted into Tears at her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and had ſcarce the Force either to blame her weakneſs, or to make her ſenſible that ſhe ſhar'd in her Grief. She at laſt aſſur'd her, that ſhe would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to her ſatisfaction as far as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſhe could, and went out to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Marqueſs <hi>Spinola,</hi> who had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verheard all their Converſation, and who was ſo ſenſibly afflicted with Grief at the Recital <hi>Peppa</hi> had made, that 'twas not difficult to be diſcern'd when the Princeſs came to him. He was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely concern'd to have bin thus long a Pretext to his Aunt for oppoſing a Paſſion both ſo real and ſo tender. He was then of the mind that if he had but known how conformable were the Sentiments of <hi>Peppa</hi> and the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> he would have taken no ſmall delight in ſerving them and favouring their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign. The Princeſs was extreamly ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pris'd
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:60133:61"/> to find her Nephew in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, but ſhe was much more ſo, when he told her that he heard all that <hi>Peppa</hi> had ſaid to her, and that he was ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly griev'd, as well for the Sorrow ſhe endur'd, as for the Death of the <hi>Chevalier.</hi> He mention'd him with the greateſt marks of Eſteem, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained to his Aunt of the trouble that ſhe had given the two Lovers. The Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs aſſur'd him that ſhe never had any Knowledge of their Paſſion, and told him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urther, that in the condition wherein Affairs were then, ſhe would have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd her Husband not to refuſe the <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier</hi> his Daughter, ſince that he lov'd her ſo entirely, becauſe it might very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably come to paſs that if the Senate did not find ſome Means to appeaſe the King, this Monarch would reduce the whole State of <hi>Genoa</hi> under his Subjection.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the <hi>Chevalier</hi> of—being inform'd that his Miſtreſs was at <hi>Turin,</hi> immediately took poſt thither: As ſoon as he was landed, he happen'd by chance to ſtop at the ſame houſe where the Marqueſs <hi>Spinola</hi> lodg'd. Our Marqueſs preſently knew him, and was ſo ſurpris'd to ſee a man whom he was inform'd was dead, that he look'd at him ſeveral times without ſaluting him, imagining that he was miſtaken by the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:60133:61"/> Reſemblance of ſome Features. The <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier,</hi> who judg'd by the ſurprize of the Marqueſs that he had knowledge of his Paſſion, did not forbear coming up to him, and ſaluting him very civilly. He then told him, that he was perſwaded that the ſame Affair was the cauſe of both their Journeys to <hi>Turin.</hi> The Marqueſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>lling himſelf out of the Surpriſe he was in, return'd the Complement to the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> and declar'd to him that (wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving whether or no they came both upon the ſame Errand,) he knew, that for his part, he eſteem'd no Buſineſs more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant, then the care he always took to contribute to his happineſs. He gave him an Account of the Report that was ſpread abroad of his Death, by what means he had heard the particulars of his Love towards his own Miſtreſs, of the deſpair <hi>Peppa</hi> was in, and of the extraordinary Reſolution that ſhe had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, to leave the World, and to ſhut her ſelf up for ever in a Convent. The <hi>Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier</hi> hearken'd with infinite ſatisfaction to <hi>Peppa</hi>'s Reſolution, which ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently juſtified the Strength of her Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; but having heard that ſhe was ſick, and that no body was permitted to enter into her Chamber, he believ'd it a very difficult thing for him to ſee her, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:60133:62"/> having the Princeſs <hi>Doria</hi> againſt him, who had in Proſpect what was whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppoſite to his Love. The Marqueſs left him ſtill in his Error, and without letting him know that the Princeſs would be more favourable to him than he could imagine, he only promis'd him that he would find out ſome means to introduce him ſecretly to <hi>Peppa.</hi> This Promiſe put the <hi>Chevalier</hi> into a great Extaſie. He embrac'd the Marqueſs, who left him to go ſpeak to the Princeſs. She appear'd to him much concern'd that <hi>Peppa</hi> ſtill perſiſted in her firſt Reſolution, and was continually preſſing her to be carried to the Nunnery of the Annunciation. The Marqueſs told her that he was juſt come from a Gentleman whom he had known at <hi>Rome,</hi> and whoſe fame was very great for his Ability in curing any Diſtemper of the Mind, and that if ſhe pleas'd, he would bring him that he might give his Opinion of the deſpair and trouble which <hi>Peppa</hi> labour'd under; and he would aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure her before hand, that this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man would diminiſh much of her trouble aſſoon as ever he had but ſpoke to her. The Princeſs who was ſtill far from ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the Miſtery that the Marqueſs hid from her, conjur'd him to bring this Gentleman the very ſame day. She ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:60133:62"/> ſo many things concerning the Joy ſhe ſhould receive, if ſhe could but give <hi>Peppa</hi> as great an occaſion now to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend her, as formerly ſhe had reaſon to be diſpleas'd, that the Marqueſs <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nola</hi> thought he might no longer diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the happy Rencounter that he had made. He was reſolv'd however to know, before he told her that the <hi>Chevalier</hi> was living, if ſhe would really favour his Paſſion, as ſhe declar'd how much ſhe wiſh'd to have been made ſenſible of it before. He turn'd the Diſcourſe to the Affairs of <hi>Genoa;</hi> and after he had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agerated the Importance thereof, he told her that he had heard from very good hands, that a general Peace was agreed on, none having had ſo much care for the Intereſt of the Republick, as to ſee that <hi>Genoa</hi> ſhould be included, the <hi>French</hi> King having reſerv'd to himſelf what puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he had deſign'd them, that this caus'd in him a great deal of Fear for his Countrey, and ſhe might hereby ſee that the Marriage of <hi>Peppa</hi> with the <hi>Chevalier</hi> of—would have been very advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous to her Family. The Princeſs who admitted all theſe Reaſons of her Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew to be very ſubſtantial, aſſur'd him that ſhe ſhould not have oppos'd it, if the Correſpondence that the <hi>Chevalier</hi>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:60133:63"/> had with <hi>Peppa,</hi> had but been known to her. <hi>Since that you are in this mind,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied the Marqueſs, <hi>it depends now upon you to oblige the Republick with a Protector, who has no ſmall Power in the French Court, and engage</hi> Peppa <hi>to you by an everlaſting Acknowledgement, and to do an Action which will Crown you with Glory. The</hi> Chevalier <hi>of—is not dead; and to conceal nothing from you, 'tis he that I intend to bring to</hi> Peppa, <hi>under the name of the Gentleman of</hi> Rome, <hi>who is Maſter of ſuch great Secrets in Phyſick. The Intereſt of our Republick, as well as the Eſteem that I have for him, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades me to propoſe to him that he ſhould marry</hi> Peppa <hi>privately; and methinks by all the Reaſons which I have urg'd, you muſt needs receive a great ſatisfaction in being favourable to the Paſſion of two Perſons who have lov'd ſo long and ſo tenderly.</hi> Altho' the Princeſs <hi>Doria</hi> was convinc'd with theſe Reaſons of her Nephew, ſhe was notwithſtanding in a great Perplexity. She fear'd to take upon her an Affair ſo nice; but the Marqueſs ſtill alledg'd ſo many Reaſons, and ſo earneſtly beg'd her to grant him the Favour which he ask'd, that ſhe promis'd at laſt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the Union of theſe two Lovers. She would however let <hi>Peppa</hi> take the Pleaſure of the ſurpriſe, and told the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:60133:63"/> Marqueſs that without letting her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eive the leaſt notice of the Truth, ſhe would propoſe to her only to ſee a Man who would engage for her Recovery. The Marqueſs return'd to find out the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> who upon the hopes of the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance promis'd, did now ſuffer a moſt tormenting Impatience for the ſight of him. He aſſur'd him, that he ſhould quickly ſee <hi>Peppa;</hi> and the Thanks that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he receiv'd for it, convinc'd him ſo much of the true Paſſion he had for her, that he believ'd he might now be plain with him. He therefore councell'd him, ſince that he was ſo much in Love, to think of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving a ſecret Marriage, and not to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe any longer a Paſſion ſo true, ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocal, and ſo tender, to the uncertain Events of Fortune, which might ſtill pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce new Obſtacles. He promis'd him further, that he would make all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt he could with the Princeſs <hi>Doria,</hi> in his Favour. The <hi>Chevalier,</hi> who durſt not have extended his Hopes ſo far, was charm'd with this Promiſe; and embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the Marqueſs, told him, That this was giving him more than a Life, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the Princeſs, that ſhe would let him marry <hi>Peppa.</hi> They continu'd a long Converſation together, and the <hi>Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier</hi> ſhew'd ſo fervent a Paſſion, that the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:60133:64"/> Marqueſs had much a-do to forbear diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſing what Sentiments the Princeſs had for him. Judge to what great exceſs was his Joy, when that the Marqueſs having gone out the next morning, return'd a little while after, he told him, That he had diſcours'd with his Aunt, and that having let her know that he was ſtill not only alive, but that it was his higheſt Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition to make <hi>Peppa</hi> ſenſible of his Love, by any Obligation whatſoever that might be propos'd to him, he had found her diſpos'd to agree to all that he could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect. His Happineſs appear'd ſo little credible, that he was long in doubt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no his Senſe of Hearing was as good as it us'd to be. He made the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs repeat over again ſeveral times the Aſſurance he had given him of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent he had obtain'd of the Princeſs. The Service that he had done for him, exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his Acknowledgments, made him that he did not know how to leave off re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning Thanks, which he expreſs'd with a Zeal that ſufficiently teſtify'd the ſtrength of his Paſſion. It was indeed too violent, to let him defer any longer the ſeeing of the Princeſs <hi>Doria.</hi> He conjur'd the Marqueſs to carry him to her, and he had all the reaſon in the World to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy'd with his Reception. She aſſur'd
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:60133:64"/> him very obligingly, That ſhe would not have perſwaded her Daughter-in-law to marry her Nephew, but that ſhe was ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant that ſhe was pre-engag'd; and that when ſhe had heard of the ſecret In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence that had paſt between them, ſhe lamented his death, which put it out of her Power to make amends for the Diſquiets whereof ſhe had been the cauſe. She added, ſmiling, That ſhe much fear'd that <hi>Peppa</hi> was not in a Humour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his Viſit; becauſe ſhe had menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd him as a Man admirable in curing ſuch Diſtempers that all other Phyſicians had not the leaſt Knowledge of; to which all the Anſwer ſhe receiv'd, was, That far from admitting of a Cure, ſhe ſhould die with Grief, if ſhe did believe her ſelf capable of receiving any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. <hi>I believe,</hi> continu'd the Princeſs, ſpeaking to the <hi>Chevalier, that ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains ſtill in the ſame Reſolution of not ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you. I'll once more try if I cann't ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed this time, then you ſhall uſe the Power you have over her.</hi> In ſpeaking theſe words ſhe conducted the <hi>Chevalier</hi> to her Daughter's Apartment; and leaving him in the Anti-chamber with the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs, ſhe went in to <hi>Peppa,</hi> who had kept her Bed two days. She in vain endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to make her conſent to the Viſit
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:60133:65"/> they came to make her. <hi>Peppa</hi> remain'd all along obſtinate in refuſing. <hi>It is not juſt,</hi> ſaid the Princeſs to her, <hi>to have that Complaiſance for you, as to let you die without help.</hi> At theſe words ſhe order'd one of her Women, who waited, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce the Gentleman that was in the Anti-chamber, and who had boaſted to have a ſure Remedy for her Diſtemper. <hi>Peppa,</hi> whom her Sorrow made always wiſh to be alone, and who could not comprehend, that there could be any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy for a troubled Mind, where the Body ſuffer'd not, complain'd of the Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence that ſhe impos'd upon her; and perceiving a Gentleman enter her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, ſhe turn'd to the other ſide, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſo much as looking on him, being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to make no Anſwer to any of the Queſtions that he might ask her about her Illneſs. The Princeſs convinc'd more and more of her real Grief, pleas'd her ſelf with the thoughts of the ſudden change that ſhe would find in her condition; and ſtepping towards the <hi>Chevalier, I'll leave you all alone with the ſick perſon,</hi> ſaid ſhe to him, <hi>The reſtleſs condition wherein her Diſeaſe has caſt her, having made her averſe to all manner of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, I perceive ſhe deſigns not to hearken to you; but I hope, that ſince you are maſter of
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:60133:65"/> ſuch an infallible Secret, as I have heard reported, you have alſo Skill enough to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade her to make uſe of it.</hi> She went out in ſaying that, to her Nephew, who at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in the Anti-chamber, till 'twas time for him to come in. In the mean while the <hi>Chevalier</hi> approach'd to the Bed, where his Miſtreſs lay, and for to oblige her to turn towards him; <hi>What,</hi> ſaid he to her, <hi>cann't all my earneſt deſires of offering you my Service, merit ſo much as one look? Have you ſuch great reaſon to hate your life, that nothing in the World can oblige you to preſerve it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words letting her hear a Voice like that of her Lover, caſt her into a Diſorder which is impoſſible to deſcribe, ſhe thruſt forth a ſigh at the remembrance of his loſs; and not daring to believe that the news of the <hi>Chevalier</hi>'s death was falſe, ſhe remain'd ſtill in the ſame condition, without looking towards him that ſpoke to her. <hi>In the name of Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> continu'd the <hi>Chevalier, diſdain not my Care. What fatal Reſolution ſoever you have taken, perhaps you may change it, if you will but admit of my Aſſiſtance.</hi> He pronounc'd theſe words with an Accent ſo tender, that <hi>Peppa</hi> trembling, and in diſorder, turn'd at laſt towards him, and raiſing her Eyes up to his Face, ſhe knew
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:60133:66"/> again all thoſe Features, of which her Heart was but too full. <hi>You live then,</hi> ſaid ſhe to him, with a feeble and unaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd Voice, <hi>may I believe my Eyes, and am I not in a Dream? I do live,</hi> anſwer'd the <hi>Chevalier, and while you ſee that all my Endeavours are to be with you, you would be unjuſt, if you did not believe, that I live only for you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We muſt no longer believe it poſſible to die with Joy, ſince <hi>Peppa</hi> could ſuffer the Emotions which a ſight ſo dear, and ſo agreeable caus'd in her. The <hi>Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier</hi> tranſported with Love, told her in the moſt obliging and ſofteſt terms, That he was not in a condition to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate openly the greatneſs of his Paſſion, but he would ſacrifice to her his All, and never part from her more. The Liberty that now was permitted them to ſpeak without Conſtraint, gave them the opportunity of declaring what they had ſuffer'd for one another, they made a thouſand Proteſtations of an everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Conſtancy; and their Converſation had not been ſo ſoon finiſh'd upon a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject ſo inexhauſtible, if the Princeſs, who was impatient to participate in their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, had not entred with her Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew. <hi>Peppa</hi> at that moment began to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon what her Grief had often
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:60133:66"/> made her ſpeak in her hearing; the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance hereof put her into a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion that would ſcarce let her look up. The Princeſs <hi>Doria</hi> diſſipated this trouble, in declaring to her that ſhe might fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Dictates of her Heart, and that far from oppoſing the happy ſucceſs of a Paſſion that ſhe ſaw ſo well eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, ſhe brought her Nephew to her, who renouncing in favour of the <hi>Chevalier</hi> all the Pretenſions that he had made formerly, came now to aſſure her that he aſpir'd but to this only Advantage of being receiv'd as a Friend to them both. The Marqueſs <hi>Spinola</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd this Aſſurance by all that the moſt real and ſincere Friendſhip can inſpire in a generous Heart; and <hi>Peppa</hi> full of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement for ſo great an Inſtance, anſwer'd him with all the eſteem that he could expect. The <hi>Chevalier</hi> who was owing to his Aſſiſtance for the favorable Sentiments of the Princeſs, expreſs'd himſelf again to him in all the obliging things that could be ſaid to a Friend to whom one is infinitely bound; And as his Paſſion made him proteſt that he would never more leave his lovely Miſtreſs, the Princeſs <hi>Doria</hi> interrupted him, by let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him know, that for both their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts his return to <hi>France</hi> was indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable.
<pb facs="tcp:60133:67"/> She added, that, not to let him have any juſt occaſion of being any longer diſquieted, ſhe would have him marry her Daughter-in-law be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his departure, not doubting but that after the manner ſhe deſign'd to write to her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, ſhe ſhould eaſily gain his Conſent, which was neceſſary thereto; but that for ſeveral Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which reſpected the one and the other, ſhe judg'd it moſt proper, that this Marriage ſhould be kept ſecret, and that they ſhould not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it till after that the Affairs of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick were come to ſome Concluſion with the King. It is very needleſs to ſay any thing of the Joy that the two Lovers receiv'd from a Propoſition which would raiſe them to ſuch a State that was the final Object of all their Wiſhes. The imagination of thoſe who never had their hearts touch'd with Love, can't poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly penetrate far enough to conceive the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of ſuch a joy. The Princeſs <hi>Doria</hi> wrote to her Husband, and the Chevalier took upon him the care of diſpatching a Courier to <hi>Genoa.</hi> His quick return ſhew'd that 'twas Love gave the Orders which were executed with ſo much diligence. He brought the Conſent which they expected, and the two Lovers enjoy'd the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of being at laſt united, after ſo many Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacles with which their Paſſions had been croſs'd.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:60133:67"/>
            <head>BOOKS Printed for, and Sold by <hi rend="blackletterType">M. Crook</hi> at the <hi rend="blackletterType">Green-Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> nigh <hi>Devereux-Court.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>DIVINITY.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>BRevis Demonſtratio,</hi> being the Truth of the Chriſtian Religion proved by <hi rend="blackletterType">Reaſon,</hi> in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Price bound, <hi>10d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi rend="blackletterType">The Proteſtant Religion the ſafe way to Salvation;</hi> or an anſwer to a Book Entituled, <hi>Mercy and Truth, &amp;c.</hi> Together with the <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Inſtitution of Epiſcopacy. As alſo <hi rend="blackletterType">Nine Sermons</hi> on Special Occaſions; by <hi>W. Chillingworth,</hi> the <hi>5th.</hi> Edition. To which is now added Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi>'s Reaſons againſt Popery, to perſwade <hi>Mr. L.</hi> to return again to the <hi>Church of England,</hi> in <hi>fol.</hi> price bound <hi>14s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi>'s Book as before made more generally uſeful, by <hi>Mr. P.</hi> with ſome Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, in 4to. Price bound <hi>7s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. The Doctrine of <hi>Paſſive Obedience,</hi> Delivered in a Sermon on the <hi>30th.</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> by <hi>J. Ellesby</hi> of <hi>Chiſwick, 4to.</hi> price <hi>6d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. A Diſcourſe about <hi>Conſcience,</hi> in relating to both the Extreams of Popery and Fanaticiſm. <hi>Id.</hi> in <hi>4to.</hi> price <hi>6d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Mr. <hi>W. Howell</hi>'s Viſitation Sermon before the late Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter, 4to.</hi> price <hi>6d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Dr. <hi>G. Haſcard</hi> Dean of <hi>Windſor</hi> his Three Sermons, one upon the <hi>5th.</hi> of <hi>November,</hi> the other two before ſeveral Lord Mayors, in <hi>4to.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb facs="tcp:60133:68"/>8. Mr. <hi>Manyngham</hi> Preacher of the Rolls, and Lecturer of the <hi>Temple,</hi> his <hi rend="blackletterType">Six Sermons</hi> Preached on Publick Occaſions, whereof two of them are on Anniverſaries, in <hi>4to.</hi> price bound <hi>2s. 6d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. A Sermon Preached at the <hi>Savoy,</hi> by Monſieur <hi>Des Eſcotais,</hi> now Printed in <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi> Twelves.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Hugo Grotius</hi>'s <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> Greek, Latine, and Engliſh, with a Praxis to it of all the Greek words therein, in <hi>8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o.</hi> price bound <hi>2s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>The Spirit of Phropheſy,</hi> proving that Chriſt and his Apoſtles were Prophets; written by the Directions, and recommended to the Preſs by the late Learned Dr. <hi>Peter Gunning,</hi> then Lord Biſhop of <hi>Ely,</hi> in <hi>8vo.</hi> price bound <hi>2s. 6d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>The King-killing Doctrine of the Jeſuites</hi> in a ſincere Diſcourſe to the <hi>French</hi> King, written by a Roman-Catholick-Gentleman, in <hi>4to.</hi> price <hi>1s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>A modeſt Plea for the Clergy</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> wherein is conſidered the Reaſons why they are contemned and ſlighted, in <hi>8vo.</hi> price bound <hi>1s. 6d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi rend="blackletterType">An Introduction to the Holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament,</hi> or a ſhort, plain and ſafe way to the Communion-Table, being inſtructions for the worthy Receiving the <hi>Lord</hi>'s <hi>Supper,</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected for, and familiarly addreſſed to every particular Communicant, by Dr. <hi>L. Addiſon</hi> Dean of <hi>Litchfield.</hi> To which is added the <hi rend="blackletterType">Communicant's Aſſiſtant,</hi> being a <hi>Collect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion of Devotions</hi> to be uſed <hi rend="blackletterType">before, at,</hi> and <hi rend="blackletterType">after</hi> the Rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iving the <hi>Holy Sacrament;</hi> price plain bound <hi>1s.</hi> guilt on the back <hi>1s. 6d.</hi> This Book is alſo bound up with <hi>Common-Prayers</hi> of ſeveral Binding, ſold by <hi>W. Crook.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">
                  <pb facs="tcp:60133:68"/>15. <hi>The Caſe of Reſiſtance</hi> of the Supream Powers ſtated and reſolved according to the Doctrine of the Holy Scriptures, by <hi>W. Sherlock</hi> D. D. in <hi>8vo.</hi> price bound <hi>2s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>Two Diſcourſes,</hi> The firſt concerning <hi>Truth,</hi> the ſecond ſhewing <hi>Popery</hi> the great Cauſe of Atheiſme, by <hi>T. Mayningham,</hi> Preacher of the <hi>Rolls,</hi> and Lecturer of the <hi>Temple. 8vo.</hi> price bound <hi>1s. 6d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>The Souls Communion with her Saviour,</hi> or the Hiſtory of our <hi>Bleſſed Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as it was written by the <hi>Four Evangeliſts,</hi> and now for the benefit of all pious and devout Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians digeſted into <hi>Devotional Meditations,</hi> by a Reverend Divine of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price bound <hi>1s. 6d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">18. Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi>'s <hi>Sermons,</hi> the laſt Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in <hi>fol.</hi> with his Life to it.</p>
               <p n="19">19. <hi>The Duty</hi> and <hi>Benefit</hi> of <hi rend="blackletterType">Frequent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,</hi> in a Sermon Preached at St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Church in <hi>Lincoln,</hi> upon <hi>Paſſion-Sunday,</hi> by <hi>W. Leightonhouſe,</hi> late Fellow of <hi>Lincoln-Colledge, Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> in <hi>4to.</hi> price <hi>6d.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>LAW.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The Juriſdiction of the Authority of Court-Leets,</hi> Court Barons, Court Marſhalſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a's, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> together with the moſt neceſſary learning of Tenures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by <hi>J. Kitchin, 8vo.</hi> price bound <hi>6s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Praxis Curiae Admiralitatis Angliae,</hi> Author <hi>F. Clarke,</hi> in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price bound <hi>1s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The Reports of <hi>Hen. Hobard,</hi> Ch. Juſt. in <hi>folio,</hi> price bound <hi>10s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb facs="tcp:60133:69"/>4. The <hi>Firſt, Second, Third</hi> and <hi>Fourth</hi> Part of the <hi rend="blackletterType">Inſtitutes</hi> of the <hi>Laws of England,</hi> being a Commentary on <hi>Littleton</hi>'s <hi>Tenures.</hi> An Expoſition of the <hi>Statutes.</hi> Pleas of the Crown, and <hi>Juriſdiction of Courts,</hi> in 4 Parts, in 3 vol. in Folio.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>The Law of Charitable <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes Reviſed,</hi> and much enlarged, with many Caſes in Law both Antient and Modern, with the reading of Sir <hi>Fr. Moor</hi> upon the Statute of the <hi>43d.</hi> of <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> digeſted by <hi>G. Duke</hi> Eſquire.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Officina Brevium,</hi> ſelect and approved forms of Judicial Writs and other proceſs, with their Returns and Entries in the Court of <hi>Common-Pleas;</hi> as alſo ſpecial pleading to Wrics, in Fol. price bound <hi>12s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>A Dialogue betwixt a Student and a Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher</hi> about the Common Laws of <hi>England,</hi> by <hi>Tho. Hobs</hi> of <hi>Malmsbury,</hi> in <hi>8vo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. The ſeveral <hi>Statutes of Bankrupt,</hi> with the Judges Reſolutions thereon.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>The Compleat Clerk,</hi> being forms of all Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents and Conveyances <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in <hi>4to.</hi> price bound <hi>12s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Les Reports des tres Honourable</hi> Edw. <hi>Seigneur</hi> Littleton, <hi>Baron de</hi> Mounſlow, <hi>Cuſtos de la Grand Seale</hi> d'Angletterre, <hi>&amp; de ſes Majeſte plais Honourable Privy Councill en le Courts del Reigne de Roy</hi> Charles I. in Fol. price bound <hi>12s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>The Compleat Sollicitor,</hi> entring Clerk and <hi>Attorney,</hi> fully inſtructed in the Practice, Methods and Clerkſhip of all his Majeſties Courts of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and Common Law,</hi> Superiour and Inferiour; as well thoſe in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> and the City of <hi>London,</hi> and elſewhere through the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> a Collection more uniform and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally
<pb facs="tcp:60133:69"/> advantageous than any extant of the ſame kind, in <hi>8vo.</hi> price bound <hi>3s. 6d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>The Reports and Pleadings</hi> to them of the late Lord Chief Juſtice Sir <hi>Edmond Saun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> Kt. in Fol. in Two Volumes.</p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>A new Book of Declarations,</hi> and other <hi>Pleadings, General and Special,</hi> in the moſt u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Actions in the Courts of King's Bench; as alſo, a Choice Collection of ſpecial Writs and their Returns, together with Obſervations in Pleading, Inſtructing the Younger Clarks in the Practice of that Court, <hi>Printed from the Original Manuſcript out of Court-Hand, to prevent the Errours that doth happen by the Tranſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> to which is added <hi rend="blackletterType">Appeals</hi> of Murther and <hi>Mayhence,</hi> with Pleadings thereon, which no other Book of this kind hath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Collected, and drawn by <hi>John Hanſand,</hi> Gent. late of <hi>Cl. Inn,</hi> in Folio, price bound <hi>10s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>Two Dialogues in Engliſh,</hi> between a Doctor of Divinity, and a Student in the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> of the <hi>Grounds of the Laws;</hi> in <hi>8vo.</hi> bound, price <hi>2s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. The <hi>New Natura Brevium</hi> of the moſt Reverend Judge Mr. <hi>Anthony Fitzherbert,</hi> Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and Reviſed; whereunto is now added the Authorities in Law, and ſome other Caſes and Notes by the Tranſlatour, out of the <hi>Year Books,</hi> and <hi>Grand Abridgments</hi> of the Law, with a New and Exact Table of the moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial things contained therein, <hi>8vo.</hi> price bound <hi>6s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>Reports D'aſcuns Caſes (qui ont evenus aux tems du Roy Henry le ſeptiéme de tres-heu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuſe memoire, &amp; du tres-illuſtre Roy Henry le huitieſme, &amp; ne ſont compriſes deins les livres
<pb facs="tcp:60133:70"/> des termes, &amp; Ans de meſmes les Roys) ſeliges hors des papieres de</hi> Robert Keiſiway <hi>Eſq; par</hi> J. Croke <hi>Sergeant al Ley, Jades Recorder del City de Londres &amp; prolocuteur del meaſon des Communes, &amp;c. Oveſque les Reports d'aſcuns Caſes priſes per le Reverend Juge</hi> G. Dalliſon, &amp;c. <hi>&amp; per</hi> G. Bendlo <hi>Serjeant al Ley, &amp;c. La tierce Edition un bellie de pluis que deux</hi> milles Reference <hi>aux autres livres Cy bien Antient que Modern de la Ley,</hi> Folio, price bound 14 <hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>An Exact Abridgment of all the Statutes</hi> in Force and Uſe, from the beginning of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> down to the Year 1689. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed Alphabetically under their proper Heads and Titles. In this Impreſſion, the year of the <hi>King,</hi> and the Chapter of every <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> have been compared with the <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Book at large,</hi> wherein many hundreds of falſe References are corrected with great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctneſs and care, to prevent the Reader's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing miſ-led as he hath been in former Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>8vo.</hi> price bound 7 <hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">18. All the 4 parts reprinted of <hi>Leonard's Reports,</hi> Fol. together.</p>
               <p n="19">19. The 3 parts of <hi>Bulſtrodes Reports</hi> reprinted, in Fol. in one Volume.</p>
               <p n="20">20. <hi>The Regiſter of Writs,</hi> new Printed, with the <hi>Digeſt of Writs</hi> added to it, and ſeveral <hi>New Writs</hi> in Fol.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>HISTORY, &amp;c.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>An Inſtitution of General Hiſtory,</hi> or the Hiſtory of the World in Two Volumes, by
<pb facs="tcp:60133:70"/> 
                  <hi>W. Howell, Dr. of Civil Laws,</hi> and Chancellour of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> in Fol.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Clelia,</hi> the whole Romance, in Five Parts, written in <hi>French,</hi> now put into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> Fol.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Scarron's Comical Romance,</hi> being an Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorical Account of a Company of <hi>Stage-Players,</hi> full of variety of <hi>Novels,</hi> rare <hi>Adventures, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous Intreagues,</hi> being Witty, Pleaſant and Profitable for all that deſign Innocent Mirth, Fol. price bound 8 <hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>The whole Series of all that hath been Tranſacted in the Houſe of Peers</hi> concerning the Popiſh Plot in 1678, and 1679. wherein is contained the moſt material paſſages in both Houſes of Parliament, relating to the full diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thereof, in <hi>8vo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. A <hi>Copy of two Journals of the Houſe of Commons. The firſt,</hi> for the Seſſions of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment begun at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the <hi>21ſt</hi> of <hi>October</hi> 1678. and continued to the <hi>30th</hi> of <hi>December</hi> next following. <hi>The Second,</hi> of the Parliament begun at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the <hi>6th</hi> of <hi>March</hi> 1678. containing the Tranſactions from the firſt day of their Sitting to their Diſſolution, in <hi>8vo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Hiſtorical Collections,</hi> or an exact Account of the Proceedings of the Four laſt Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> of Famous Memory; wherein is contained the Compleat Journals both of the Lords and Commons, taken from the Original Records of their Houſes; as alſo, the more particular behaviours of the worthy Members during all the laſt Notable Seſſions, comprehending the Motions and Arguments of the Renowned and Learned Men of that time, as <hi>Cecil, Bacon, Rawleigh, Egerton, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leigh, Buckhurſt, Walſingham, Hatton, Coke, Croke,
<pb facs="tcp:60133:71"/> Spelman,</hi> &amp;c. Laboriouſly and Faithfully Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, by <hi>Heywood Townſend</hi> Eſq; a Member in thoſe Parliaments, in Fol.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Megalopſichy,</hi> A particular and exact Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the laſt Seventeen years of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign, both Military and Civil; (being the former Journal of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Four laſt Parliaments) with Sir <hi>W. Monſon</hi>'s Account of the Wars between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> with the Number of Ships and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders at that time; to which, at the end is added Dr. <hi>Parrey</hi>'s Trial and Execution for Treaſon againſt Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> in Fol.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>The Connexion</hi> being choice Collections of ſome principal matters in King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Reign, which may ſerve to ſupply the vacancy betwixt Mr. <hi>Townſend</hi>'s and Mr. <hi>Ruſhworth</hi>'s Hiſtorical Collections, in <hi>8vo.</hi> price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>The Hiſtorian's Guide,</hi> or <hi>Brittain's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancer,</hi> being a Summary of all the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Exploits, Sieges, Battels, Deſigns, At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, Preferments, Honours, Changes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and whatever elſe is worthy Notice, that hath happened in his Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſties Dominions, from the year 1600 to 1688 ſhewing the Year, Month, and Day of the Month in which each Action was done, price bound 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>The Bucaniers of America,</hi> or an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the moſt Remarkable Aſſaults com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted of late years upon the Coaſts of the <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> by the <hi>Bucaniers</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh, Dutch,</hi> and <hi>French</hi> in <hi>Jamaica;</hi> to which is added the Second Volume, containing the dangerous Voyages, and bold Attempts of
<pb facs="tcp:60133:71"/> Captain <hi>Bartholomew Sharp,</hi> and others, in <hi>4to.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. Mr. <hi>Tho. Hobs</hi> of <hi>Malmsbury,</hi> his Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of <hi>Homer</hi>'s <hi>Illiads</hi> and <hi>Oddiſſes</hi> into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> with the Life of <hi>Homer,</hi> and a large Preface of the Virtues of Heroick Poeſie.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Mr. <hi>Hobs,</hi> &amp;c. his Poem in Latine and Engliſh, of the Wonders of the Peak in <hi>Darby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> commonly called the <hi>Devils Arſe of Peak.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. Mr. <hi>Hobs,</hi> &amp;c. His Four Tracts. <hi>Firſt Behemoth,</hi> the Hiſtory of the Cauſes of the <hi>Civil Wars in England,</hi> from the year 1640, to 1660, Printed from the <hi>Author</hi>'s <hi>own Copy,</hi> never Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (but with a thouſand faults) before, with a defence of his <hi>Leviathan,</hi> againſt Biſhop <hi>A. Bramhall,</hi> and a Narration of <hi>Hereſy,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>8vo.</hi> price bound 5 <hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14 <hi>Compendium Geographicum,</hi> or a more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act, plain, and eaſie introduction into all <hi>Geogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy,</hi> than any yet extant, after the lateſt Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries or Alterations; very uſeful, eſpecially to young Noblemen and Gentlemen, the like not printed before, <hi>with</hi> 2 <hi>Alphabets</hi> of the Names of Towns and Places, the one <hi>Antient,</hi> the other <hi>Modern,</hi> in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price bound 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>Moral Inſtructions of a Father to a Son,</hi> upon his long Voyage, being an eaſie way to guide a young man to vertue, 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price bound <hi>1s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>The Court of Curioſity</hi> being the moſt exact and Curious Book of <hi>Dreams</hi> and <hi>Fortune-teller</hi> that is extant, being much enlarged and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained in this new Edition, in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price bound <hi>1s. 6d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>The Flower-Garden,</hi> and compleat Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, being an exact <hi>Flower-Garden,</hi> and a true manner of planting all ſorts of <hi>Vineyards,</hi> in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price bound <hi>1s. 6d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">
                  <pb facs="tcp:60133:72"/>18. <hi>A Modern view of ſuch Parts of Europe</hi> that hath lately been, and ſtill are the places of great Tranſactions, <hi>viz. Italy</hi> with all is Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>France</hi> with all its Provinces, <hi>&amp;c. Germany</hi> with the Dukedom of <hi>Lorrain</hi> and all the Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, <hi>Spain</hi> with all its Dominions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with Curious Remarks of Antiquiry, <hi>8vo.</hi> price bound <hi>2s. 6d.</hi> Printed, 1689.</p>
               <p n="19">19. <hi>The Preſent State of the Jews,</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price <hi>1s. 6d.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="20">20. <hi>The firſt Eſtate of Malandiſon,</hi> in <hi>8vo,</hi> by the ſame Author.</p>
               <p n="21">21. The Tranſlation into Engliſh of all <hi>Homer's Illiads and Odiſſes,</hi> by <hi>Tho. Hobs,</hi> in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. price bound <hi>5s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="22">22. <hi>Brittains Glory, and Englands Bravery,</hi> wherein is ſhewn the degrees of Honour from the Prince to the Peſant, with the honour of the Nobles, and Priviledge of the Commons, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he proper places and precedency of all Perſons, from the Throne to the Bondman, more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly in Coronations, Feaſts, Funerals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To which is added a <hi>Continuation of the Hiſtorians Guide, to June</hi> 1689. in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:60133:72"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
